<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the most high and mighty prince, Charles the II. By the grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. An epistle written and humbly presented for His Majesties use, and enlightning of the nation. / By Arise Evans.</title>
            <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84158</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868963</idno>
  <idno type="VID">121320</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240932076</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2118_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210137</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868963</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868963e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84158)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121320)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 242:E2118[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the most high and mighty prince, Charles the II. By the grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. An epistle written and humbly presented for His Majesties use, and enlightning of the nation. / By Arise Evans.</title>
                  <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Lowndes at the White Lion in S. Pauls Church-yard, and Simon Gape next door to the Hercules Pillars in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: For His Majesties use, and enlightning of the nation.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121320:1"/>
            <p>TO THE Most High and Mighty <hi>PRINCE,</hi> Charles the II.</p>
            <p>By the Grace of God, <hi>KING</hi> of Great <hi>Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>AN EPISTLE Written and humbly presented <hi>For His Majesties use, and Enlightning of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By ARISE EVANS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Lowndes</hi> at the White Lion in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>Simon Gape</hi> next door to the Hercules Pillars in <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:121320:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121320:2"/>
            <head>FOR <hi>HIS MAJESTIES</hi> USE, And Enlightning of the <hi>NATION.</hi> The PROLOGUE.</head>
            <p>MOst glorious <hi>King,</hi> I beseech Your <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> to read through this little Book, and then I believe Your <hi>Majesty</hi> will read it again and again, and <hi>promote</hi> it; for it will quench the spirit of Rebellion, establish Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Throne, and bring all to obey Your <hi>Majesties</hi> command in unity as one man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Royal Sovereign,</hi> I have not had the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and learning fit to compose, garnish and swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with eloquent phrases of delights, an Epistle
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121320:3"/> meet for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> reading; but since I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand that Your <hi>Majesty</hi> stoops so low, as to hear Quakers, and such as scorn learning, I hope to have the like favour: It is an high presumption in such as I to direct a speech to a <hi>King;</hi> for if <hi>Moses,</hi> who was learned in all the wisdom of the <hi>Egyptians, Acts 7.22.</hi> when God sent him to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> complaineth to God, saying, <hi>he had not eloquence and ability sufficient to speak to a King, Exod. 4.10.</hi> much more may I bemoan my want thereof; and we cannot be ignorant of this, that Truth from the mouth of eloquent <hi>Apollo</hi> is more mighty to operate upon the spirits of men, <hi>Acts 18.24, 25, 26, 27, 28.</hi> than it is from the mouth of an unlearned person: But, <hi>Oh King,</hi> to what end do I thus speak? I am sensible of my wants, but not capable of a supply: Therefore I shall humbly address my self to Your Royal <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> in the best manner and method that I am able.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121320:3"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>KINGS</hi> Most Excellent Majesty.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Lorious and illustrious <hi>King,</hi> set up of <hi>God,</hi> beyond all compare in transcendent glory: If I had the tongue of men and of Angels, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not express my joy at Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restauration, for I was almost dissolved at it, and carried up to <hi>heaven</hi> in a Charriot of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>speakable joy full of <hi>glory:</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve learned how to beat down the greatest sorrow with ease, but such a joy I can hardly master. Indeed I had of all men living the most re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>son to rejoyce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, for as I may so say with reverence to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majesty of God, I had set the Truth and <hi>glory of God,</hi> Your <hi>Majesties</hi> honour and <hi>glory</hi> also, with my own repute and credit as I was Gods servant, all at stake▪ now that <hi>God</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blasphemed by wicked men, upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) <hi>for his own name sake,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould vindicate his own honour, truth and <hi>glory,</hi> Your Royal <hi>Dignity,</hi> and my self, <hi>by Your Majesties appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121320:4"/> and Restauration,</hi> was such a mercy to me, that my heart could not contain the joy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, neither could my to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gue express my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulness; but sighs and grones, mingled with tears of joy, was all I could offer to God upon that day; <hi>the glory of the Lord astonished me,</hi> so that I looked upon that day as <hi>Dooms-day,</hi> to stop the mouths of <hi>Gods</hi> enemies, Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> enemies, and mine also, who for seven years together was under the reproch of friends and foes, because I kept Your secret, according to the advice of the Angel, <hi>Tobit</hi> 12.7. for a great and effectual door was opened to me, but there were many adversaries, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.9. so that I was not ignorant of the <hi>time</hi> of Your <hi>Majesties</hi> coming <hi>personally</hi> to Your <hi>throne;</hi> yet prudence would not give way to shew it plain, for the adversaries had got too much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage against You, had they knowne the <hi>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Most glorious <hi>Soveraign,</hi> to Repeat the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acts of <hi>God,</hi> is a thing most pleasing to him, and to call to mind his former mercies, &amp; praise him for them, is the way to find mercy in time to come; the Royal Prophet King <hi>David,</hi> is our example for the said purpose, who writes and records the works of <hi>God</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that all might praise him for his mercy which endureth for ever; not only that present generation, but also the generations to come:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121320:4"/>
               <hi>Psalm</hi> 78.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7. forgetfulnesse of <hi>Gods</hi> mercies, and not Regarding the works which <hi>God</hi> hath done for us, is a great sin, that hath a damnable Judgment following it; <hi>Psalm.</hi> 28.5. my soul is troubled, because some Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists despise my words, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.19, 20. which proved so effectually for their welfare; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think it fit, to give Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Majesty</hi> a hint of what <hi>Gods</hi> providence hath brought forth for us, that we and the generations to come, might behold it and praise his name: I beseech Your <hi>Majesty</hi> to Read this book, and Consider it Diligently for your own good; for though my words be mean, yet they have been always powerfull, for <hi>God</hi> doth own them.</p>
            <p>And now to look on things past, and so come forwards, may it please Yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>Majesty</hi> to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that there was a spirit of Rebellion among a party on foot, all along from the beginning of <hi>Queen Elizabeths</hi> days to Your famous fathers time; which spirit still smo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>king and burning with fury, troubled both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> And there was an <hi>antipathy</hi> between me and it from my <hi>Child-hood,</hi> that notwithstanding the said party was mighty kind unto me, and would fain gain me to be of their side; yet I could never Consent to be of their mind, but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and Reprove them, and pray to <hi>God</hi> for power to Defeat them, because I foresaw the evil of their way.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121320:5"/>
            <p>And the said spirit though burning and smoaking was kept so low, that it could not get sufficient fuell to burn out, untill the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was cald in 1640. from that time forward <hi>there was a bridle in the jaws of the people cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing them to erre, Isa.</hi> 30.28. then it broke out into a mighty flame, and then the factious party began to show themselves, and to preach in pulpits open Rebellion; saying, that <hi>Kings</hi> were not to be Regarded nor obeyed, but the people they were the <hi>anointed,</hi> and not the <hi>King;</hi> and they despised and slandered the <hi>King,</hi> and stirr'd up the people to oppose Him, making them believe that every one was more a <hi>King</hi> then <hi>His Majesty,</hi> and bringing it to a bloody war they Cursed all that would not go out to it, or Contribute to the maintenance thereof, so that the servant maids being terrified with the Curse, were forc'd to throw their Thimbles and Bodkins into that massie heap at <hi>Guild-hall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And they preached down and destroyed, so far as they could, all fabricks erected and set up, to keep Christianity in memory. And they strove to have all the holy feasts kept for the honor of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> put down and buried in oblivion; I mean <hi>Christmas, Easter,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> suntide</hi> and their off-spring the Sectaries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> so high in Rebellion as to have the Holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Contempt, and to count that Record
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121320:5"/> of <hi>God,</hi> (which he hath appo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted to hold forth his name and <hi>glory</hi> in all ages and to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,) far inferior to a thing they call a light within them, which light falsly so called, can be nothing else but grosse da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kness and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ignorance.</p>
            <p>Thus they went on furious<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y preaching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermission, untill they brought his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Majesty</hi> to the block, and having slain him, they seized upon all belonging to the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and made it their own, and their next voice in pulpits was (after they had slain the <hi>King) prepare slaughter for His Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> had his design going on for Your <hi>Majesty</hi> all this while, that he reserved <hi>a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect</hi> part of that Parliament, from having a hand in the <hi>highest</hi> Crimes, who in time were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to defeat their brethren, and to open the way for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restoration, and these were called the secluded members.</p>
            <p>But the bold party went impudently on, that notwithstanding all their wickednesses, <hi>they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved with a high confidence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they and they only were in the favour of God;</hi> and after <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi> fight, all hopes was go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, so that most of the <hi>precious Royalists,</hi> like <hi>David, Psalm.</hi> 73. were staggering at their prosperity and successes, ready to give up their hopes, and the <hi>spirits</hi> of the people were laid-down so <hi>flat,</hi> that none durst be known to mention Your <hi>Royal name,</hi> except to reveil it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:121320:6"/>
            <p>Now things being thus, I was sore grieved, <hi>and the Lord God blessed be his name for ever,</hi> was pleased to <hi>light a candle</hi> of understanding in my heart; That I reading and searching the Scripture, as I used to do, found new things, <hi>Isa.</hi> 48.6. all promising Your glorious Restoration, &amp; coming by <hi>Gods</hi> Providence to look upon the 8. Chapter of <hi>Amos,</hi> I found the whole trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy set down in order, and in the conclusion thereof, that the Traytors should fall and <hi>never rise up again;</hi> and in Chapter the 9. of <hi>Amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> I found Your <hi>Majesty,</hi> or rather Your Royal father as He is in You set up in a triumphant <hi>manner,</hi> to destroy Your enemies and the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of Your Royal <hi>house</hi> for ever; and all this to be so easily <hi>understood,</hi> that any ordinary capacity with a little guiding might see it plain: which Chapters as I have opened them, are worthy of Your <hi>Majesties</hi> serious considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Then I went among the Sectaries, and at their several meetings I shewed those Chapters, opening it unto them, and though they were mad <hi>against me,</hi> yet could they not find argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hstand such invincible truths, for I resolved now being <hi>armed,</hi> to go in the name of my <hi>God,</hi> into all places where I could find Your <hi>Majesties</hi> greatest enemies, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw their high <hi>Confidence,</hi> and pierce their hearts with my sharp arrows.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121320:6"/>
            <p>And I wrote my exposition on the 8. and 9. Chapters of <hi>Amos,</hi> and carried it <hi>first</hi> to <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> who seemed then not to regard it, <hi>for he thought I could not get it printed;</hi> but when I gave it him in print with much more, and that he had read it, <hi>then we had a terrible bout,</hi> so that at last I drive him out of his Chamber with ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
            <p>Then I carried it Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> and he being not at home, I left it for him, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d after a few days when I came for it, <hi>Lilly</hi> was very thankfull to me, (being a stranger to him) for showing him such things, and before some Gentlemen that were with him he commended it highly, saying that he never saw better things come from a man in all his days, and he desired me to let him have it a while longer, and I left it with him, and had it again: And after my book was print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I met <hi>Lilly,</hi> who then was mighty glad of my book, and did incourage me to write more books, and follow it close, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that by that book <hi>he judged me</hi> to have sufficient ability (th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ough <hi>Gods</hi> blessing upon it) <hi>to turn the world upside down;</hi> this <hi>Lilly</hi> was civil to me, and I shewed the said exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sition on <hi>Amos</hi> to all them that were the greatest stick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers for the State, and found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t daunted their spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and courage very much.</p>
            <p>By this time my little Manuscript was grown to a pretty volume, for I added to it daily,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121320:7"/> and had many Copies to lend out, so that the sound thereof came to the ears of the <hi>Royal par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and then I was sought out and sent for by persons of <hi>quality,</hi> and my Manuscript did flye about among them, and they were much <hi>che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished</hi> and strengthned by it; but yet I found no ease, because I could not get it Printed for the benefit of all; I offered it to Booksellers, but could find none that durst print it, yet I found that money would bring it out.</p>
            <p>Then I made my moan to many persons of worth and <hi>quality,</hi> who said, They could wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly part (for so good a work) with so much money <hi>as I needed,</hi> but durst not do it, lest it should be known, and that by thence assisting of me they should forfeit to the Rebels <hi>their lives and estate,</hi> such a fear they were in.</p>
            <p>But it pleased the <hi>Almighty God,</hi> (that my Manuscript going from hand to hand) by his <hi>divine providence</hi> to order it so, that it came at last to the hand of a Gentleman of <hi>Grays</hi> Inne, by name Mr. <hi>William Saterthwayt,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Exchequer, of great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>integrity, full of charity and good works, and a mighty over of Your <hi>Majesty;</hi> the same Gentleman being so great a lover of Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> must needs come and see me for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> sake.</p>
            <p>And coming, a friend being with him, they call'd at my door, whereupon I went to them,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121320:7"/> and the said Gentleman gave me my Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script in such a <hi>manner,</hi> that I did admire at his <hi>grace</hi> and humility; but yet desiring to be <hi>soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> I shewed him no countenance; and as we were parting, the other Gentleman seeing that, said to me, Come and take a glass of <hi>wine,</hi> it will do you good, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you are very sad; and as they compell'd me, I went with them, and coming to a Tavern, where we drank one pint of <hi>wine,</hi> they asked me why I was so sad? I told them it was because I could not get my Manuscript printed; for, said I, if it were prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it would operate much for His <hi>Majesties</hi> advantage, otherwise it will be but of small ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. Mr. <hi>Saterthwayt</hi> answered, if you think so, then take no care for that, said he, for I will have it printed whatsoever it costs me: when he said so, my heart leapt for joy.</p>
            <p>And then I looked upon h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, not as a man, <hi>but an Angel of God sent to relieve me;</hi> for the night before, about the same <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime, I had pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>God</hi> to ease me, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end one speedily to help me to have my book printed, and <hi>God</hi> heard me, <hi>and sent this blessed man</hi> within 24. hours to do it; (it was a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t mercy, blessed be <hi>God</hi> for it) and he gave me forty shillings in hand to go about it, and appointed me to come to him the next day, for to go seek one to print it; and we went and found one, and had it out in print <hi>quickly;</hi> and then I began to be <hi>famous</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121320:8"/> among the people, but I did not esteem it, for I knew what I had to do, and that a cloud of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach was yet to come upon me.</p>
            <p>And when my Book came out, I gave it <hi>Cromwell, Bradshaw,</hi> and to all I could find of Your <hi>Majesties</hi> greatest enemies, and I spread it among the Souldiery both Horse and Foot; my manner was this with them; I knew the time of their going to the Guard, and as I went with them, <hi>I asked one question,</hi> he would give me a civil answer, and to gratifie him <hi>I gave him a book;</hi> he being on his march had not time to see <hi>what I gave him;</hi> and I slipt to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a good way off, gave him one after the same manner, so I gave them books, and I knew when they came to the Guard they did read them: And there was a time set in the same book for the dissolution of the Parliament, <hi>Cromwell</hi> and the souldiers through Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence brought that to pass.</p>
            <p>Then I became mighty <hi>famous,</hi> for all the people both high and low, that had seen my book or heard of it, beholding the effect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, came to me so thick, that I was not able to answer them, <hi>but gave them books,</hi> to the poor <hi>gratis,</hi> the others paid me, and all their enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was, <hi>to know what time Your Majesty would come in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time I had printed another book, in which book, upon good consideration, I had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121320:8"/> set down the year 1653. for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> comming into power and poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ssion, though not <hi>personally,</hi> and I knew the time of Your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>personally,</hi> as I shall make it appear by two witnesses.</p>
            <p>My first witness is the holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> my se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond witness is a <hi>Prophesie</hi> of a thousand years standing, signed by both our Welch <hi>Merlins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Scripture,</hi> I believed, and do believe Your <hi>Majesty</hi> to be that <hi>David</hi> which <hi>God</hi> promised to raise, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.24, 25. <hi>Hos.</hi> 3.4, 5. Therefore I concluded that Your <hi>Majesty</hi> was not to come in and reign <hi>perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> until You came to the Age that <hi>David</hi> began to reign in, and that is 30. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.4. and I made it clear in my book called, <hi>The Voice of King</hi> Charls <hi>the Father to King</hi> Charls <hi>the Son,</hi> pag. 7. that Your <hi>Majesty</hi> would come in at 30. years of Age, and I cited 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.4. to prove it; but I durst not say so much till 1654. then was I not regarded.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Merlins</hi> prophesie is as followeth, say they, when the year of Christ comes to be, 1660. Then verily <hi>Owen</hi> will come, with his sword of steel will he come, and the moon from <hi>Sivern</hi> bank shall bring <hi>Owen</hi> in his hand. Then wars shall never come to the land of <hi>Katwg,</hi> let all take notice of the time, so much the <hi>Merlins</hi> say.</p>
            <p>This prophesie Your <hi>Majesty</hi> shall find in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121320:9"/> pag. 87. of a book Called <hi>Brittish and outlandish prophesies,</hi> Printed by <hi>Lodowick LLoyd,</hi> and sold at his shop next to the Castle in Corn-hill <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and put forth by <hi>Thomas Pugh,</hi> an adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, in 1657.</p>
            <p>In the said prophesie Your <hi>Majesty</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Owen,</hi> because ye descended from <hi>Owen Tudor</hi> grandfather to <hi>King Henry</hi> 7. and the moon that is said to bring Your <hi>Majesty</hi> in, is his Excellency Generall <hi>Monck</hi> who came from <hi>Puderig house</hi> in <hi>Devonshire</hi> not far from <hi>Sivern</hi> sea.</p>
            <p>Now I looked always upon Your <hi>Majesties</hi> entrance into Your Dominion in a two-fold manner, <hi>First,</hi> Your coming in to have power in 1653. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Your coming in <hi>personally</hi> in 1660. Touching the last I have spoken, now it remaineth that I should shew how Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> came in at 1653. <hi>And this I affirm and say,</hi> That in that instant of time, when <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> did signe his Excellency General <hi>Moncks</hi> Commission for <hi>Scotland, Oliver,</hi> under God, became the prime Instrument to bring Your <hi>Majesty</hi> into power; and in that instant of time General <hi>Monck</hi> set foot in <hi>Scotland,</hi> Your <hi>Majesty</hi> had gower and possession, <hi>for he minded your work:</hi> All this came to pass in the year 1653. let this serve all for my vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Now had I declared this in 1653. when I
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121320:9"/> was so <hi>famous,</hi> the Enemies would not have suffered General <hi>Monck</hi> to go to <hi>Scotland;</hi> or had I then declared that Your <hi>Majesty</hi> would come in <hi>personally</hi> at 1660. the Enemies would have armed themselves against the time, that Your <hi>Majesty</hi> should not have been able to come in as You did, God be praised; and my setting of 1653. for Your <hi>Majestis</hi> coming in did <hi>baffle</hi> the Enemies, for seeing nothing of it come to pass, by degrees they grew careless, <hi>that by Gods providence</hi> they fall out among themselves to make way for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restaūration.</p>
            <p>And therefore I was resolved to lose my <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> among men for seven years time, and suffer reproach; so that I, my Wife and Children could not go no where, but we were mocked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised <hi>for Your Majesties sake;</hi> which if Your <hi>Majesty</hi> knew all our sufferings, You would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us greatly: And all this came upon us because I kept Your sectets, and went in a sure way to work, for in such a case I was to use <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy</hi> as well as <hi>Prophesie,</hi> else I had spoiled all Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Game.</p>
            <p>For all Gods Promises or Prophesies are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth upon condition of using the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed means to obtain them. I could make a long Discourse of this, but I leave it in short to Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Royal consideration, and go forward.</p>
            <p>I have written many little books, in which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121320:10"/> there are some things put on purpose to draw the Sectaries to read them, in hope to bring them to obey Your Majesty, for the scope of all my books is to press them to it; many of the <hi>Royal party</hi> were offended at me for such things, and specially about <hi>Cromwell,</hi> because I affirm'd that he should bring You in, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the way to be by marriage, but I found those books more effectual for Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties advantage, than any other books; and <hi>Cromwell</hi> was more offended at me for those books, (for alwayes I was aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onted by his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, after I sent them to him) than he was when I wrote point blank against him.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Cromwell</hi> knew that my perswading the Army, and those people which he most depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon, to believe that Your Majesty and he were such enemies one to the other, that ye could not agree, and that Your Majesty should come in and destroy him: I say he knew such perswasion was the onely way to strengthen him, and make his Party keep close to him for to withstand and keep out Your Majesty; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.21.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, <hi>Cromwell</hi> knew that my perswading his Party to believe that he would bring in Your Majesty, would be the onely way to make them jealous of him, and to fall away from him, as they did, to his and their ruine; now all this time I durst not mention his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121320:10"/> General <hi>Monck.</hi> neither in any books nor in discourse, till his coming last winter to <hi>London,</hi> then indeed I wrote an Epistle to him, to have him bring in Your Majesty.</p>
            <p>For the People, though they did reproach me, yet they constantly enquired of me, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>When will His Majesty come?</hi> but I was forced, as the <hi>Prophet saith,</hi> Isa. 30.1. <hi>to adde year to year</hi> for it, and so keep them in hope; for I durst not declare otherwise; and last win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I was like to spoil all with one word.</p>
            <p>It was this: I being at a booksellers shop (a friend of mine) in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, and a Company of General <hi>Moncks</hi> souldiers being newly come to Town, stood before the Shop door; the mistress of the house calling me <hi>false Prophet,</hi> said, <hi>Now there is no hope that ever the King will come in;</hi> No, said I, <hi>pointing at the Souldiers,</hi> There is them that will bring him in: A fellow hearing me, goes to the Souldiers and tells them what I said; whereupon they being mad at that, came fierce upon me, saying, <hi>Do you say that we shall bring in the King?</hi> and they were ready to pull me in pieces, for then the Parliament (so called) were at the height: Gentlemen, said I, you are under <hi>command,</hi> you cannot do it of your selves, but do you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your Leaders. This would not satisfie them, but they were ready to seise upon me; by providence of God, at the instant the man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121320:11"/> of the house coming suddenly in, and finding them in and about his door, asked them rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and boldly, <hi>What had they to do there?</hi> and being daunted by him they fell back and I sli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t away.</p>
            <p>But put the case I had been taken Prisoner, and that the matter had come before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Army and Parliament, it might have disappointed General <hi>Monks noble purpose,</hi> and brought forth a sad consequence; but this God did, to shew, that my former <hi>prudence</hi> in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Your Majesties secret was good, and that my hasty speaking <hi>imprudently</hi> might have spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all, had not God (to him be the Glory) by his providence prevented it. I beseech Your Majesty and all others consider it.</p>
            <p>And to go back and come forward in order, when I came with books to <hi>Cromwell,</hi> the Commanders of the Army coming about bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness to him at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and finding me there, did many times set upon me in their way of Dispute, (in which way I was sufficiently versed, having been often at their meetings) that many times we disputed four hours toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; sometimes I had a dozen at once to speak to one after another, as they could frame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments against Your Majesty, and I, having <hi>truth</hi> on my side, foiled them all, and some being mad at it were ready to run me thorow with their swords, saying, <hi>Why should we suffer such
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121320:11"/> a man to live and speak such words to weaken our hands, and to strengthen our enemies?</hi> others would have sent me to prison: for all that they would take my books, and give me not a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them.</p>
            <p>But still there stood up a party for me, which said to them, <hi>The man speaks no railing language, he speaks with good words what in conscience he believes to be true, and you know we are for liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conscience, if you can convince him do, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise let him go;</hi> but I never did depart from them so long as they had a word to say to me upon that account; and I am sure that I s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke <hi>ten times</hi> more home for your Maj. among them at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> and at other meetings, than I spake in all my books, <hi>for they put me to it;</hi> and I would not leave them to carry it aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, <hi>but stood to it,</hi> and their hearers did so <hi>sigh</hi> and <hi>groan</hi> at it, seeing me alwayes come off victor, that I spoiled their meetings, God strengthning me, and giving me at an instant what to say unto them, <hi>blessed</hi> be his <hi>name</hi> for ever and ever, and I believe I g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve forty pounds in books amongst them.</p>
            <p>I had many worthy persons that stood to me all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his while, and helped me with money to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>intain my Family; but chiefly that good and pious Gentleman Mr. <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erthwayt,</hi> the true lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Your Majesty, as I said before, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r godly Gentleman, a tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lover of Your Majesty also, by name Mr. <hi>Samuel Starli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g;</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:121320:12"/> these two, under God, were my chief friends that never failed me, but gave me money at all times when I needed it, because I did Gods work and Your Majesties; and I hope Your Majesty will remember them, if occasion be, for indeed they have merited Your Majesties fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as I could make it appear at large, but I would be brief.</p>
            <p>I cried up <hi>Lambert</hi> the last year with a loud voice, saying, <hi>That he should bring in Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> but once I was like to be brought to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> called <hi>The bad Lord Mayor of London,</hi> for it, yet the Witnesses could not agree about it, one saying, <hi>He did not heed what I had said;</hi> the other had a brother great with <hi>Lambert,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would have had me suffer for disgracing his Lord <hi>Lambert,</hi> and make the Army and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries to be jealous of him; <hi>my Lord broke that share,</hi> as abovesaid, and I escaped.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Lambert,</hi> if it be rightly considered, did Your Majesty the last and greatest service in the field; for the Sectaries depcnded so much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, that they thought at last if they could get him out of the Tower to stand in the field, all was their own; for they made account that he should prevail, and that then the Parliament would steer their course another way, and not bring in Your Majesty. But <hi>Lambert</hi> getting out, and being many dayes in the field, yet could get no considerable party, is taken and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121320:12"/> brought up prisoner again: <hi>This deaded the hearts of the Sectaries,</hi> and made the Parliament go on couragiously to bring in Your Majesty with all speed: Now I know not what thanks is <hi>Lambert</hi> worthy of for that good service, State-policy is a deep thing, and <hi>Lambert</hi> is made (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what I said) a great instrument to bring in Your Majesty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Most glorious Sovereign,</hi> I spake alwayes (as guided of God) those things that I knew would most effect for Your Majesties advantage, and my wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds by some were counted ridiculous, yet they are words of truth, though not alwayes to be understood in a vulgar common sense, but as it is made out in the aforesaid business of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> and to proceed in order.</p>
            <p>In <hi>September</hi> last 1659. when <hi>Lamberts</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and the Parliament so called began to strive about superiority, I had certain visions which shewed me what would become of them; the visions as I wrote them then are as followeth: <hi>September</hi> 22. as I was in a trance, I heard a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the people, saying, <hi>That the King was with an Army up towards Windsor, but no war in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended;</hi> and as I went to the <hi>Thames</hi> side, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h an intent by water to go and see the <hi>King,</hi> the side of the <hi>Thames</hi> towards <hi>Southwark run up with a swift course,</hi> and the other half of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver run down, so that the Water-men and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wondred at it, saying, <hi>We have seen two
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121320:13"/> tides in a day, but such a thing was never seen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the water being thus high tide, the one side running up, the other running down, for a day together, is a great wonder;</hi> and many went up by water to see the <hi>King,</hi> and some that I knew beckned their hands that I should not tell of their <hi>going,</hi> for methought they were in great fear; and as I did get up methought toward <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> I returned back, and as I was <hi>alone</hi> marching toward home, with a bright, drawn, long Knife in my hand, I met a grim <hi>woman</hi> in sad-colour clothing, who made toward me furiously, but as she saw my Knife, <hi>she tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and fled away</hi> from me; then methought I was on horseback, and rid till I came near <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Southward, and there in a little village near the River I met my wife, and as we came to take water the <hi>Thames</hi> was dried up, so that one might cross it and not go over shoes, and the bancks were grown with Grass <hi>to four yards breadth,</hi> in which the River ran, and methought it was not a quarter of a yard deep in the <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel,</hi> and as I was reasoning with a Water-man about it I awoke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> 23. in a trance I was with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that pleased me well, and going a little way from them, with an intent to come to them again, I heard a melodious noise of <hi>musick</hi> in the dead of the night, and my thought it was the City Waits that played to the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121320:13"/> methought it was their custom to play so every night, and I saw them having their Instruments in their hands, and play in their beds, for their Chamber was low, and they had a candle, and I was at their window; <hi>then I left them,</hi> and as I went seeking my company it was day-light, and I came to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace where an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Bricklayers, Labourers, and such men, were building an high brick <hi>tower,</hi> and making fine walks, and as I turned about and looked upon the tower again, on a sudden the builders were all gone, not one to be seen; then I asked <hi>a man</hi> that was all alone, and trimmed a green banck, <hi>belonging to an old great house,</hi> which stood on a hill over against the brick building, <hi>Why they left work?</hi> said he, <hi>Because it is Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day noon:</hi> but he went on trimming the <hi>banck</hi> till it was on the back like a creature, then at last he with his great strength did take it in his arms and raised it up on end, by that it had a lively face like a <hi>woman,</hi> and then I began to praise the Workman, saying, <hi>Never did any Limner the like;</hi> but as I looked on it, the said <hi>banck</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>came a perfect woman indeed, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and walking about her business, and having her maid, which rose with her, to attend her: At which sight I was amazed, and said, <hi>Surely this is Gods work;</hi> and then meeting with some of my company, and telling them what I had seen, with much joy I awoke.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121320:14"/>
            <p>Now having these <hi>Visions</hi> I thought good to stir about with them, and see what <hi>Gods</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would bring forth by them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.18. and because I would not intrude to go and see the Great Ones of the times <hi>without some law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful occasion by their account,</hi> I wrote a few lines and had them drawn <hi>fairly,</hi> to get their hands for a place at the <hi>Custom-house,</hi> and I went to them to have their hands, being assured they <hi>durst not</hi> subscribe to any thing under my name.</p>
            <p>First, I went to the then Lord General <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thal,</hi> (it was on the fifth of <hi>October</hi> 1659. the day before the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>City</hi> feasted the Parliament (so called) and the Army) and gave my Paper to <hi>Lenthals</hi> Secretary, and he brought it me again, saying, <hi>His Lord would not signe it;</hi> I told him, <hi>that I would not take his answer,</hi> and immediately <hi>Lenthall</hi> came down, and I shewed it him, and spake to him; said he, <hi>I am going now to the Parliament, come at three a clock and I will speak with you.</hi> From thence I went to <hi>Fleetwood,</hi> he was sick, none but Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries must come nigh him; I sent him my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and he sends me a fine smooth denial. Then I went to <hi>Lambert,</hi> and he answered me proudly, saying, <hi>that his Lordships hand was not to be had at so cheap a rate; Hasilrig</hi> told me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, <hi>that he did not love to have his hand lye in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender:</hi> such expressions they had.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121320:14"/>
            <p>Then at three a clock I came to <hi>Lenthall</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and with much ado among others I got to him, and he told me he would not put his ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to my Paper at that time, but, said he, I will speak for you to some of the Commissioners of the Customs to morrow at the feast, and after that come to me again: and two dayes after I came to him, and he bid me stay.</p>
            <p>And when all the company was gone, for it was <hi>Saturday</hi> at night, he tooke me aside, and said, <hi>Do those Visions of God continue with you, as formerly they did?</hi> Yes, said I; said he, <hi>Can you tell what will become of us?</hi> said I, yes, that I can; and I tell you no good will come of you, except you <hi>bring in the King;</hi> otherwise there will be nothing, but one will be getting up, and others will be pulling him down, and confusion and destruction of all will follow. <hi>It is true,</hi> said he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if we go about to bring in the King, can you shew us any assurance from God that we shall bring it to pass?</hi> Yes, said I, and I told him my Visions as they are above written, and did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret them to him; indeed he could discern the meaning of it as well as my self: Then said he, <hi>this gives no assurance that we shall make our peace with the King, have you had any Vision to that purpose?</hi> Yes, said I, and it hath been printed this half year: said he, <hi>I never saw it, pray let me hear that:</hi> then I began as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121320:15"/>
            <p>I shall shew you a Vision that I had in <hi>June</hi> 1634.</p>
            <p>Being in a trance I saw my self standing in a Pool of water in <hi>Merionethshire,</hi> at the parish of <hi>Talylun,</hi> and as I stood upon the water I saw a company of black Foxes pursuing a young Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as they followed the Lion they ran round about me, sometimes on the water, and sometimes on the high way, that is on the North side of the Pool; I pitied the Lion, and cast stones at the Foxes with all my might; but as I was throwing stones at the Foxes, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately they appeared to be young Children, and stood still a while on the way, the North side of the Pool, and a voice said to me, <hi>Why dost thou cast stones at the children?</hi> and as I came to Land, immediately they turned to be black Foxes pursuing the Lion again; but on a sudden the Foxes being on the water became white Lambs, stood still, and the Lion being on the water turned to them, and they, as it seem'd to me, kissed each other. Thus the vision ended.</p>
            <p>The Interpretation is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>KING CHARLES</hi> is the Lion, and you are the Foxes, the stones are the words of my books against you, your becomming Children was your Dissolution by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which made you repent th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you did not before make your peace with the <hi>King;</hi> your turning to black foxes again signifieth that you are the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121320:15"/> same now as ye were before your Dissolution; your turning to be white Lambs, is that you shall seek for peace to the <hi>King;</hi> and your kis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing each other, signifieth that you will effect it, and settle peace in a glorious manner.</p>
            <p>Then was <hi>Lenthall</hi> much satisfied, and said, <hi>We have human learning enough, and we can guess at things to come, but we look upon you to have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Revelations from God; I pray when any more is revealed to you let me know it.</hi> So we parted that time.</p>
            <p>The week following they made three Acts, one to turne out <hi>Lambert</hi> and eight more Commanders of the Army with him, the other to put Commissioners over the Army, the third, that no money should be raised without consent of the people in Parliament; and <hi>Lenthall</hi> was the main man in devising and making of these Acts: Now these Acts divided Your Majesties Enemies, and shut up the purses of Your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that neither the pretended <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> nor that Parliament, could raise any money to pay the Army, and made way for his Excellency General <hi>Monck</hi> and a <hi>free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to bring in Your Majesty; and <hi>Lenthall</hi> did partly fore-see the consequence of those Acts when they were made.</p>
            <p>Now after the Parliament (on the thirteenth of <hi>October</hi> 1659.) was Dissolved by <hi>Lambert,</hi> I went often to <hi>Lenthall,</hi> who told me that now
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121320:16"/> he wanted power; said I, be faithfull and stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you will soon come to your power again. Then he sent his Letters about and was not idle, and when he had his power again, it was he that sent for general <hi>Monck;</hi> it was he that sent the Army out of <hi>London</hi> to give place to general <hi>Monck</hi> and his Army, and did many more things for Your <hi>Majesty</hi> worth respect: The man is nothing to me, for I neither eate nor drink at his cost, nor had a penny from him all that time; only I do love him, and do this for him because he regarded the things of <hi>God,</hi> and acted for Your <hi>Majesty</hi> accordingly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then over Your Dominion in power above all.</p>
            <p>On the first of <hi>March</hi> 1659. as I met <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thall</hi> in <hi>Westminster-hall</hi> comming from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament house, I gave him these <hi>Visions</hi> as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>February</hi> 21. 1659. the day after the Seclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Members sate in Parliament, I beheld that my head was cut off I knew not how; and laid down upon a table before me, and I admired how I could see it and live as I did without my head: But withall finding my self not well or like to continue alive so, I speedily with my hands wiped the face thereof which was a little soild, and set it upon my neck in its right place again; and then I thought I was at first a little heavy-headed, but presently my head was so
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121320:16"/> setled that I felt my self better then ever I had been afore in all my life, I saw no bloud spilt or any bloud in all the Vision, <hi>to God be the glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The interpretation:</p>
            <p>My body is the Nation or Parliament, and specially the secluded Members which seems by the circumstance of time to be the life of all; my head is the <hi>King,</hi> and doubtless as I wiped my face and set up my head seeing a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity of it, so shall you speedily set up <hi>King Charles</hi> Steward, and you shall see such a necessity of Him, that you and the Nation cannot possibly live without him; and you shall do it without any bloud if you hasten it, but take this Vision also from <hi>God;</hi> that if you do not hasten to bring in <hi>King Charles,</hi> you will be ruined all in bloud afore you are aware of it, for ye have the subtil, restless Sectaries among you that endeavour to bring it so to pass according to a <hi>Vision</hi> that I had <hi>February,</hi> 27. 1659. which is as followeth.</p>
            <p>I perceived I was not well in my body, and as I opened my cloathes to see it, my shirt was all bloudy, then I thought some one had given me privately a mortal wound with a bodkir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or small pen-knife or some such thing, which I thought was within my body. In this also I signifie the Nation and Parliament, therefore have a care you be not surprized. Thus much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121320:17"/> I gave <hi>Lenthall</hi> Verbatim as abovesaid, and I saw him no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e untill <hi>May</hi> 4. 1660.</p>
            <p>Now I thought in regard of his great service, that <hi>Lenthall</hi> should have been the greatest man of that party in <hi>England,</hi> except General <hi>Monck,</hi> whose name ought to be for his Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Recorded with Letters of Gold; but hearing the report that <hi>Lenthall</hi> was out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Sequestred, I was amazed at it and went to see him, when I came to his sight, said he to me am I now at the lowest? said I, how came you to be so, had you no correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with the <hi>Kings Majesty</hi> all this while? no, said he, I durst not send to him for fear of <hi>marring all,</hi> if it had been known it would have done i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Said I that spoild you, but however <hi>God</hi> knowes what you did for His <hi>Majesty,</hi> he will reward you, and in due time I shall shew of it as much as I can for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and I hope it will be for your honour. <hi>God</hi> will not have such good deeds go unrewarded, and He will inform the <hi>King</hi> that His <hi>Majesty</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward you. In the mean time I will acquaint my very good friend Sir <hi>John Greenfeild,</hi> (now Earl of <hi>Bath</hi>) with a hint of it: said he, I pray do, so we parted and I wrote to the Earl for him.</p>
            <p>After that he lost his place at the <hi>Rolls,</hi> but see the hand of <hi>God</hi> upon it, he that had his place is soon taken away by death, as if <hi>God</hi> by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121320:17"/> it should say to Your <hi>Majesty</hi> thus, you knew what service the Lord <hi>Culpeper</hi> did for You, therefore he had Your favour, and You made him <hi>Master of the Rolls;</hi> but You knew not what <hi>Lenthall</hi> did for You, who was put out, <hi>therefore behold my hand for him;</hi> and I say, though <hi>Culpepper</hi> was faithful to Your <hi>Majesty,</hi> yet if he had had Your three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms in his hand, as once <hi>Lenthall</hi> had them, it is a question whether he would have hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to rhe Counsel of <hi>God,</hi> and done as <hi>Lenthall</hi> did: I beseech Your <hi>Majesty</hi> to take it into Your Royal consideration.</p>
            <p>An honest man may meet theeves and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and go with them, being forced to feign himself a thief, and so save his life and purse; yet when any opportunity comes he will make his escape, and bring them all to the hold: and this was Mr. <hi>Lenthalls</hi> case; for I believe he had alwayes a good heart towards Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty,</hi> but could not shew it till God gave the opportunity.</p>
            <p>It was a special providence of <hi>God</hi> for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Exaltation, that kept in <hi>Lenthal</hi> to go on with the Sectaries until these times; he was alwayes right for you, and so prudent, that the Sectaries could not be without him: Such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence is not to be forgotten, for <hi>Lenthall</hi> was great in power, and accordingly did he act for Your <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121320:18"/>
            <p>And it was also a mighty providence of <hi>God,</hi> in General <hi>Monck</hi> and many others, some did for Your <hi>Majesty</hi> (though not willing) out of envy to the House of <hi>Cromwell,</hi> as <hi>Fleetwood, Lambert, Desborough,</hi> and many more suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; others of pure affections, as noble <hi>Monck,</hi> worthy <hi>Len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall,</hi> and several beside them; as it was <hi>Phil.</hi> 15.16, 17, 18. and all for Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> advantage, as it proved: These acted, yet in the dark.</p>
            <p>For, had not <hi>God</hi> by his special providence sent me the aforesaid Visions in <hi>September</hi> 1659. when the Parliament and Army were at a difference, and had not I gone to <hi>Lenthall,</hi> and he listened to me as he did, then I tell Your <hi>Majesty</hi> what was like to come to pass; and it was partly in agitation, as may be seen by the Diurnals of that time: The Parliament and the Army had agreed for <hi>Fleetwood</hi> to go to be chief in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Lambert</hi> likewise chief in <hi>Scotland,</hi> noble <hi>Monck</hi> removed, as <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Harry, Cromwells</hi> Sons, were; and <hi>Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thall</hi> to be Lord Paramount in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let us <hi>glorifie God</hi> for those Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and think that <hi>Lenthall</hi> and I have been his Instruments to turn the stream another way for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restauration; and <hi>God</hi> never faileth in sending means to bring to pass what he hath determined or forespoken, as it is here seen, the Visions of <hi>God</hi> with my holding them
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121320:18"/> forth to <hi>Lenthall,</hi> who was at the stern, turn'd all for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Exaltation.</p>
            <p>It is true, many Ministers are against <hi>Vision</hi> and <hi>Dreams,</hi> and I my self am against superflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that nature; but yet I say these Visions were so seasonable and so suitable to the affairs of our Nations, shewing what the issue of things then on foot would be, that I may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly say twenty of those Ministers all agreeing to preach long Sermons before <hi>him,</hi> would not have perswaded <hi>Lenthall</hi> so much as these Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions did, for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restauration and the good of the people thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> saith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.18. <hi>Where there is no Vision the people perish:</hi> I am sure it was verified in this our time, and had not <hi>God</hi> sent these Visions, these three Nations had come to a sad end. And though General <hi>Monck</hi> meant well, what could he have done while <hi>Lenthall</hi> was in power and command above him? again, if any other man had told <hi>Lenthall</hi> such Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he had not believed him; but he having experience of the truth of my former <hi>Visions</hi> and <hi>Books,</hi> did both enquire and believe what I said: to <hi>God</hi> be the <hi>glory</hi> of it; I prayed for <hi>wisdom,</hi> I acted by it, I desired Visions, and all for Your <hi>Majesties</hi> sake; seeking nothing for my self all the while: And now I hope Your <hi>Majesty</hi> will do something for me.</p>
            <p>And now I come to speak for my self: Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121320:19"/> my condition at this time, as to matter of outward substance, is worse than it was before Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Restauration; for my friends of the Royal party, that helped me heretofore, now say to me, <hi>You must go to the Kings</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o doubtless will make you a great man, in regard of your faithful eminent service done to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, we will do no more for you:</hi> and I am old, and so weak for the want of outward comforts, that I am not able to work if I had it, so that I am <hi>cast by Gods providence</hi> wholly upon Your <hi>Majesties</hi> Grace, as a child is left to his Fathers care, for food and rayment.</p>
            <p>Again, the Sectaries (for this cause) glory over me, saying, <hi>Ah, now, you have your King, but what are you better for it? If you had done so much for the Parliament as you did for him, they would have done for you, and you might have had a great estate, and been more capable of his favour (if he had come in) than now you are; for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing all you did for him in hope of great things, you are in the same condition still, and like to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a poor man; he will not look upon you, for now merits are not weighed in the ballance of the</hi> Sanctuary, <hi>and favours are not equally distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but it is bought and sold, he that gives most money is preferred, and the Kings poor faithful friends, that have done most for him, go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> witness your self for one; <hi>the Parliament abhorred such doings, and God and all good men do hate it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121320:19"/>
            <p>My answer to them is this, <hi>His Majesties</hi> Revenues for the present are in Hucksters hands, and so is the Estate of all his friends, especially those <hi>Nobles</hi> that came over with him, have nothing <hi>left them;</hi> these <hi>Nobles</hi> having the disposing of places, <hi>are forced</hi> to make the most of them to subsist for the present, but when <hi>His Majesty,</hi> and His <hi>Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> have their own again, <hi>as I hope the King and Parliament will quickly bring it so to pass,</hi> then shall you see places will not be sold, and that things in Church and State will be so well carried on, that neither you nor your Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in any age have seen the like hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>And for your saying, <hi>That</hi> His Majesty <hi>will take no notice of His poor servants,</hi> That is not true, for I meeting His Majesty walking in Saint <hi>James's</hi> Park, upon my bare relating of my name, His Majesty called me to Him, gave me his hand to kiss, promising to remember me; which, I hope, will be by raising my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune beyond mine enemies expectation; and having an evil humour that did disfigure my face much, the very touch from his <hi>blessed hand</hi> (for I did not kiss it because my mouth was fore) wrought such an alteration in my body, that on a sudden <hi>the humour was gone,</hi> and my Neighbours knew me not by face, and yet Mr. <hi>Knight,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> Chyrurgeon, said it was not the <hi>Kings-evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121320:20"/>
            <p>And now I am speaking to You I will speak further, and though it be not handsome to <hi>speak</hi> to You in an Epistle directed to the <hi>Kings</hi> Majesty, yet I hope it will be as well taken as intended; for I would not be, to separate the <hi>King</hi> from his People, nor to draw the People from Him; but I, <hi>God</hi> enabling me, shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to unite the Body to the <hi>Head,</hi> or the <hi>King</hi> and his People, and bring the Sectaries, who are furthest off, to return and be united to <hi>His Majesty</hi> and the Church of <hi>God:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take notice of <hi>Gods</hi> work done before the eyes of all the world, and before our eyes in particular.</p>
            <p>First, consider how <hi>God</hi> permitted that Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyon and destroyer to drive out the <hi>King,</hi> and to keep him out by bloudy war and shedding innocent bloud; and that nothing done in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to bring in <hi>His Majesty</hi> by war did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper, so that most men thought and said, That there was a fate upon that <hi>House,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> had cast off that family for ever: <hi>But men know not Gods thoughts, Isa.</hi> 55.8, 9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. for when you thought that all was most sure in your hands, and had provided an Oath of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration</hi> against that Family, then the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth for it, and brings in the <hi>King</hi> miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously, so that not one drop of bloud is spilt in <hi>His Majesties</hi> Restauration: <hi>This was the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes, Psalm</hi> 118.22, 23.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121320:20"/>
            <p>Secondly, consider that all the Kingdoms in the world had their beginning by war and bloudshed, so that all the Founders thereof wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded through bloud to their Thrones; but this of ours is <hi>a new Kingdome</hi> with <hi>a white Throne, Rev.</hi> 20.12. set up of <hi>God</hi> in a new way (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloud) not known before: As it is written <hi>Psalm</hi> 2.6. <hi>I set my King upon my holy hill of Sion:</hi> The Lord Jesus doth own him, <hi>for the Lord is the Lord of peace,</hi> 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.16. and now the <hi>King</hi> is not to hold his Kingdom <hi>onely</hi> as it descended to him by a Royal descent, but to hold it as it was given him (in a new way) of <hi>God blessed for ever,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, consider the Battle by which this Conquest came: It was not a Battle <hi>with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused noise, and garments rolled in bloud;</hi> but it was a Battle <hi>with burning fuel of fire, Isa.</hi> 9.5. It was the fiery zeal to <hi>Gods glory</hi> that first broke out in the heart of noble G. <hi>Monck,</hi> then in the hearts of the <hi>Royal Parliament,</hi> that made the <hi>Royal City of London,</hi> and all <hi>England,</hi> to be in a flame of Bonfires with mirth and joy; which fire did consume the wicked, and brought forth this Kingdom of <hi>glory, Heb.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28, 29.</p>
            <p>I am confident you have prayed earnestly to <hi>God</hi> for this his glorious appearance, but why do you not believe it now it is manifest, and repent of your dead works, calling for mercy to <hi>the Lord
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121320:21"/> and the King?</hi> for I may not separate them, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.21.</p>
            <p>And now I shall speak touching the Church of God, and decide the Case between <hi>Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> and <hi>Presbytery</hi> so called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Episcopacy</hi> is of <hi>God</hi> set in order according to a military Institution or way; the <hi>Archbishops</hi> are Generals, the other <hi>Bishops</hi> are Colonels, the rest of the Clergy are Officers and Captains under them, all to act in their order, and obey their Superiours, else to be cashiered. Now the true way of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> as it is spoken of in Scripture, is this; That when these are by their Superiours called together, to consult about the affairs of the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> (as sometimes the General of an Army doth in their affairs) then all those Ministers being met make a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, according to Scripture and Reason; but none (be his parts never so good) is to stir out of his Rank, except he be called to it by the Superiour Power; <hi>For God is the God of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and not the author of confusion, as it is seen in all the Churches of the Saints,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. and such are in a fit posture to stand for <hi>Christ,</hi> and to maintain his <hi>Church</hi> every one in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct.</p>
            <p>But our Presbyters, that refuse <hi>Bishops,</hi> are like a confused tumult, or at best like an Army <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t hath neither a General nor Colonels, that when any occasion cometh of standing for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121320:21"/>
               <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Chuch,</hi> they are divided and fight one against another, some turn Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, others turn otherwise, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but confusion follows; as we have seen it sufficiently manifested in these our dayes.</p>
            <p>Now I have spoken touching the true go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, and of our Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian false disorderly way of Government, I will shew the different way of their Reformation from Popery.</p>
            <p>Our true <hi>Sion</hi> and Church of <hi>England</hi> was reformed by the <hi>Kings</hi> command, and when Queen <hi>Mary</hi> reigned, they did not take up arms against her to maintain the Reformation, but yielded their bodies to suffer for the truth sake, waiting upon <hi>God</hi> for deliverance, and so it pleased <hi>God</hi> to cut off that cruel Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in a short time, and to set up Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> to restore his <hi>Church,</hi> and to comfort his people.</p>
            <p>But the false Presbyterian <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> was not so reformed, for when their Ministers would have had a Calf with a White face, or somewhat done, they knew not what, nor yet do: Then their Queen <hi>Mary</hi> understanding their design, prudently sends for <hi>John Knox</hi> and other Ring-leaders of their sedition, and they did not obey their Queens Command, but contrarily stirred up the people to rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst her, bringing it to a bloudy War, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121320:22"/> spilling of innocent bloud; thus they reformed or builded the false <hi>Sion</hi> with bloud, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet saith, <hi>Micah</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. <hi>Therefore it shall be destroyed and plowed like a field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But some will say, <hi>Queen Elizabeth sent them aid, therefore she was partaker with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer, No; but the Queen understanding that a great Army of Frenchmen was to come to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to assist Queen <hi>Mary</hi> against the Rebels, and upon their request Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> sends an Army of Englishmen to fight the French, lest they mastering the Rebels should come to invade <hi>Engl.</hi> she sent not to countenance their Rebellion or Sedition, but for the defence of her own people committed to her charge, as you have it more at large in <hi>Holinsheads</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of <hi>Scotland, pag.</hi> 371. that sheweth touching those affairs. Let this stop the mouth of such Objectors.</p>
            <p>And now to come to speak something touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Worship, <hi>Bowing at the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> and <hi>before the Lord at the Sacrament,</hi> which <hi>Bowing</hi> the Presbyters call Idolatry and Superstition, and they would prove it out of the Law, and specially by the second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to speak the truth soberly, yet mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, for <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> loveth mirth, as I shall prove hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now I would fain know, Whether the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> or the Presbyters doth best under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121320:22"/> the Law of <hi>Moses?</hi> if you grant to King <hi>David</hi> that Prerogative, as I believe you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it, then we will see what he saith, <hi>Psal.</hi> 95.6. <hi>O come let us worship, and bow down, and kneel before the Lord our maker:</hi> Surely King <hi>David</hi> was no Presbyter, else he had never done this, to bow and kneel, and bid all the Worshippers of the <hi>Lord</hi> do it also; a Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hates it. But, methinks, I hear King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and all Protestants with him, say, O ye foolish, brutish Presbyters, <hi>We do not bow before any false god, but before the Lord our maker, we bow before the Lord our maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> furiously seconds him with his sword drawn in his hand, saying, You Presbyters, will not you <hi>bow at the name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus?</hi> Yes, forsooth, we <hi>bow</hi> the knee of the heart: <hi>Who seeth that,</hi> ye bloudy Presbyters? <hi>ye lie,</hi> we see what you do: have not I said, <hi>That at the name of Jesus every knee should bow?</hi> mark, <hi>Every knee should bow, Phil.</hi> 2.10. and do you think to put it off, saying, <hi>We bow the knee of the heart,</hi> (when your actions prove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) you shall <hi>bow</hi> the knees of your bodies, <hi>else your legs shall be cut off,</hi> and then where are your knees? Do not you know, that by <hi>Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Kneeling, Prostrating</hi> or <hi>Falling down before him,</hi> Worship is done to God? and there is no Worship without such manifestation found in all the Scripture: Do not you see how God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121320:23"/> is Worshipped under the Gospel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.16. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.4. Now, you Presbyters, if you would know how to Worship <hi>God,</hi> learn of these, they all along <hi>fall down upon their faces</hi> to Worship God, yet you will not <hi>bow the knee</hi> before him, or at the <hi>great and dreadful Name of</hi> JESUS: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God is come to judge you for these things.</p>
            <p>It is clear that you Presbyters Worship the <hi>Dragon</hi> and the <hi>Beast;</hi> for <hi>mark,</hi> they that Worship the Beast do not <hi>fall down, bow</hi> or <hi>kneel</hi> before him, (that is out of doors with them, the Devil is grown cunning, he matters not that) their Worship is to praise him for his bloudy acts, in killing the Saints and people of God; that is their manner of Worship, and that Worship pleaseth the Beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.4, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Now, Presbyters, Was not that your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Worship, namely, to give thanks for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Servants of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King?</hi> Wi ness your many dayes of <hi>Thanksgiving</hi> yet upon Record: Whereas on the contrary, the late famous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious <hi>King,</hi> when Word was brought to <hi>His Majesty,</hi> that his Forces had killed some of you, and a motion made to him for a day of <hi>Thanksgiving, No,</hi> said <hi>His Maiesty, not for killing of men, I have the loss on every side, for they are my people.</hi> And God is displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121320:23"/> with such a Worship, and with such bloudy Worshippers; he bid: them <hi>not come to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence with their hands full of bloud, Isa.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. thus the good <hi>King</hi> did disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of their motion.</p>
            <p>And now I shall speak (if God permit) tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Surplice</hi> and those holy Garments, with which the Presbyters are much offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>It is true, the <hi>Surplice</hi> is not a fit Garment for a Butcher, because it will trouble his armes and hands, and comes under his feet when he stoops to kill a Beast: Therefore <hi>John Knox,</hi> and the rest of the Presbyters, when they tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Butchers of men, they cast away their <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices,</hi> for it hindered their Work; because bloud, or any spot and soyl, is soon seen upon the <hi>Surplice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But our Ministers of the <hi>Church of England</hi> used it, and kept their Garments undefiled; and as for the <hi>Surplice</hi> and those holy Garments used in our <hi>Church,</hi> we understand that they were used in the <hi>Church of Christ</hi> all along from the Apostles time: And such Garments they had under the <hi>Law,</hi> as we see they had a rich embroydered <hi>Ephod</hi> for the <hi>High-Priest,</hi> and Linnen <hi>Ephods</hi> also for their other <hi>Priests, Exod.</hi> 39. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.18. but we take it not from the <hi>Jews</hi> manner, though much alike, for the Garments of the Angels, or men (as <hi>Mark</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:121320:24"/> and <hi>Luke</hi> calls them) that first preached <hi>Christ</hi> after his Resurrection, are described for our imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; <hi>Luke</hi> saith they had <hi>shining garments, Luke</hi> 24.4. in imitation of that our embroyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Copes</hi> were made, which we had in the Cathedral Church to be worn on high dayes, as <hi>Christmas, Easter</hi> and <hi>Whitsontide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the other two Evangelists say, <hi>They were Angels in white rayment, Mat.</hi> 28.3. <hi>John</hi> 20.12. but <hi>Mark</hi> tels us, <hi>that it was a long gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and after that fashion is the <hi>Surplice</hi> made, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.5. and if you would know what this long Garment was made of, <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet will tell you that it was made of Linnen; for that Gospel-preacher, sent to shew him what came to pass in our dayes, had a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, Dan.</hi> 12.6, 7. and the seven <hi>Angels</hi> that routed the Beast, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. were all sent forth cloathed in their <hi>fine linnen Surplices, Rev.</hi> 15.6, 7. And I pray consider to what end did the Evangelists describe the habits of those first Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-ministers, which spake to the Women, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. <hi>John</hi> 20. but to give a pattern to all Gospel-ministers that were to come. We read of several <hi>Angels</hi> sent to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular persons, but nothing spoken of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits; now the Presbyters suppose that Cloaks were the holy garments which the Apostles u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to minister in; and Why, say they? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had a Cloak, therefore they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121320:24"/> use to pray, preach, and do all in Cloaks.</p>
            <p>I answer: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was a great Traveller, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26, 27. and had need of a Cloak to shelter him in foul Weather; and it being fair Weather he had left his Cloak at <hi>Troas,</hi> yet he thought good to have it brought to him against Winter, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13, 21. now if it had been Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Ministerial garment, he would not have left it behind him at <hi>Troas:</hi> Therefore doubtless in those <hi>Churches</hi> that were setled in order then, they had such garments as we used formerly in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and we had it from them all along downward by Tradition; and of that Tradition the Apostle speaks, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Cloak was not such a long one as the Presbyters use to go in, for such a long Cloak was not fit for a foot-Traveller, and of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> horse there is no mention made: We have an old saying, That <hi>the Devil used to appear in a long black Cloak to hide his cloven foot:</hi> and I met him once in such an habit, on <hi>Good Friday</hi> at night by <hi>Black Friers</hi> Church in 1644. I thought he was a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Minister, and justling with him, as I passed on, he fell under my feet like a black Cloak spread upon the ground and vanished before me: as you have it at large in <hi>pag.</hi> 121. of the first impression of my book called <hi>The Eccho to the Voice from Heaven:</hi> and as the Presbyterian
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121320:25"/> Ministers delight to follow the Devils fashion in all things, so they will have long Cloaks also.</p>
            <p>I shall speak a little of Musique, which the Presbyters cannot abide, specially to have it in the Church.</p>
            <p>But how beautiful was the Worship of <hi>God</hi> in the Quire in our Cathedral <hi>Churches,</hi> where <hi>God</hi> was worshipped in the beauty of Holiness, <hi>Psalm</hi> 29.2. <hi>Psalm</hi> 96.9. with songs, and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>God</hi> according to the injunction of <hi>David, Psalm</hi> 105. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.4, 5, 6, 42. with voices and all Instruments of Musique. Truly when I was a chjld I found Musique so effectual, that I may say it was the first <hi>moving cause</hi> that brought me to be well affected with coming to Church, and tempered my spirit to listen to the Preacher, and I believe it will much work to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose on all Children: Therefore I beseech <hi>God</hi> to send us our Quires of <hi>Angels</hi> again.</p>
            <p>It was a bold attempt of Satan, when once he tried <hi>Gods</hi> way of Musique to draw men to worship an Image; but he got such a wound by it, that he could never abide Musique neither before nor after; for the three Children, who though they loved the musique (yet hated the Idol) would not fall down to Worship the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, but rather chose to be cast into an hot fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery Furnace; out of which Furnace <hi>God</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, (<hi>Daniel</hi> 3. from <hi>vers.</hi> 12. to the end
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121320:25"/> of the Chapter) and so wounded the Devil, that King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> and all the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers, seeing the miracle, forsook him and praised the true <hi>God, Dan.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. Therefore the Evil spirit is and was alwayes an hater of Musique.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Lord</hi> loves Musique and comes to it, for the <hi>Lord</hi> comes to <hi>Elisha</hi> when the <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strel</hi> played before him, and not before, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.15, 16. here it is evident that the <hi>Lord</hi> loves Musique and comes to it.</p>
            <p>Again on the contrary, the Devil departed from <hi>Saul</hi> when <hi>David</hi> played on the Harp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. here it is evident that the Devil hates Musique and flieth from it.</p>
            <p>I am sure you Presbyters hate Musique, for you would have none in the <hi>Church,</hi> nor any where else, by your <hi>good will,</hi> as you have fully manifested when you had power; but do you not see now, by what I have shewed you, what spirit you have, and shall not I with the Finger of God cast it out? Truly I shall by Gods help cast it out whether you will or no: I had a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible sign of it, as I shewed before, and the Word of <hi>God</hi> which I hold forth to you is able to do it, and will you not repent and turn to <hi>God?</hi> And if you would have <hi>God</hi> to come to your Churches and Countrey, have plenty of Musique, then <hi>God</hi> will come to you, and drive away the Devil from you.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:121320:26"/>
            <p>Again, see Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would have men that want Instruments of musique, to learn Spiritual songs and sing them, to make melody at all times to the Lord in their hearts, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.19. And you see how the <hi>Church</hi> under the Gospel is set forth, and is said to worship God with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of musique, even <hi>Harps, Rev.</hi> 5.8, 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.2, 3. for indeed under the word <hi>Harps</hi> here is signified all sorts of musique, and the <hi>Harp</hi> hath the preheminence, because <hi>David</hi> with it drive away the Devil from <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. and a company of good <hi>Harpers,</hi> play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all at once together, make the most <hi>melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> noise in the world; but it is no loud mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sique, therefore <hi>Organs</hi> and such like loud mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sique are most fit for the <hi>Church,</hi> that all may hear and <hi>rejoyce in the Lord, Psalm</hi> 150.</p>
            <p>And truly you Presbyters Ministers, this is a great sign that you shall fall and come to nothing:</p>
            <p>This time twelve-moneth there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove six seen in <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndon</hi> streets that wore <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical coats</hi> and <hi>girdles,</hi> but now we may see six hundred in such habit, that the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> may say as it is written <hi>Isa.</hi> 49.21. <hi>Who hath begotten me these?</hi> and wonder seeing so many, where they were all this time, and say, <hi>These were the hidden ones of God, which are now come forth to rout the Presbyters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will fall a Preaching, and <hi>stir up the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121320:26"/> people, Acts</hi> 6.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.50. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.2. in your wonted way again: Have a care, and be sure the people will not believe you, for they know what evil you have brought upon them, for believing your rebellious lying Doctrine the last time, you shall never be able to preach them up to war for you again, but beware of hanging; for the same Prophesie that saith, <hi>King Charles</hi> should come in at 1660. and that there should be no more Wars, saith also, that after his coming in there shall be nine Halter-moneths, and then the old Cathedral Churches should be repaired, as you have it in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>Thomas Pughs</hi> book <hi>pag.</hi> 150. and you may believe it better than your own Preaching; for it is a certain truth, and you shall find it so, if you go on in your Rebellious wayes as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>For there is but one <hi>Anointed</hi> on earth at one time, and he that curseth <hi>Meroz</hi> must curse it, for not coming out to the help of the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> against Rebels; for <hi>Abraham, Isaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> being heads of their Families and people of <hi>God,</hi> were every one, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the <hi>Anointed</hi> for their times, <hi>Psalm</hi> 105.15. for the word is no where set down the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> to signifie many, but the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifieth but one, (as you have it throughout the Scripture) for <hi>Barak</hi> was the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> when those words were spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121320:27"/>
               <hi>Curse ye Meroz, Judg.</hi> 5.23. and they were therefore cursed that did not help the Lord with <hi>Barak:</hi> but now the Gospel saith, <hi>Curse not, Rom.</hi> 12.14. therefore you erre in holding it forth, and you are not Preachers of the Gospel; our Ministers of the <hi>Church of England</hi> never used that Text in all the time of the war.</p>
            <p>Again, I say the People were <hi>Anointed</hi> as long as they continued their obedience to the <hi>King,</hi> for the Oyle ran down from the head to the feet, that is from the <hi>King</hi> to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of his Subjects, (as the Oyntment that was upon the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> ran down to the skirts of his garments, <hi>Psalm</hi> 133.2.) but when the People were divided and cut off from the <hi>King,</hi> by your perswading of them to rebel, then the holy Unction came no more upon them; yet on those which continued <hi>loyal</hi> it remained, and that <hi>Anointing</hi> did teach them and confirm them, (though you did deprive them of their Teachers) so that you could not seduce them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19, 20, 26, 27.</p>
            <p>Now Presbyters and all other Sectaries, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess your sins before <hi>God</hi> and all the world, (for your sins are publique) that you may be glorious penitentiaries, and call to the Lord, the King, and the Countrey for mercy, all which you have offended, and return again to your true mother and true Church of <hi>God,</hi> the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121320:27"/>
               <hi>Church of Eng.</hi> to give thanks to God for giving you the grace of Repentance unto life; and do not you foolishly and childishly look upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing to be an Idol, as your brother <hi>Theaura John</hi> did send to call his friends to him in Saint <hi>Georges</hi> fields, and after he had talked a while to a great company of them, he had a fire made, and he burned his <hi>Bible,</hi> money, arms, cloaths, and all that he had, saying, <hi>they were Idols:</hi> I say, do not you do so, for we of the <hi>Church of England</hi> are sufficiently cautious in that matter of <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Superstition,</hi> and we will worship nothing but God onely. Thus much in love to you, hoping it will not be in vain.</p>
            <p>A word to describe the Presbyters and Sectaries.</p>
            <p>They are very just in their dealings, true in their Promises, they will not swear, lie, nor be drunk; and excellent qualities they have in their dealings between man and man, onely they will deal so hard, that a poor man cannot get water to his hands by them; but they pay just, and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shall not find the least sin in them, for they sin not by <hi>Retail</hi> but by <hi>Whole-sale,</hi> and their Conscience being nice and curious in smal matters, and not at all in great things; they make no Conscience to swear, and oft forswear themselves, to und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>King</hi> and Countrey; they make no Conscience to wrest the sword out of their <hi>Kings</hi> hand, though they might know
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121320:28"/> that he is the great Servant of God, even the <hi>supreme Sword-bearer of God,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. they make no Conscience to kill their <hi>King,</hi> and to take all from him and his; they make no Conscience to kill Gods Ministers, and rob his Church; they make no Conscience to destroy thousands of great and <hi>noble Families</hi> for their <hi>loyalty</hi> to God and the King; they make no Conscience to pretend to the People to take away Patentees, but in the mean time lay upon them Excise, Seisments and Taxes, an hundred times greater: These things they can do and not be troubled at it, but if they leave Six pence unpaid to a rich man, O their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science is so troubled till they pay it! and in their words they are most heavenly, that men say, <hi>they are mighty honest, just and godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, indifferent Reader, are not these th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y our Saviour speaks off, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.24. <hi>That will strain at a gnat and swallow a cammel?</hi> Truly these are they, for we do not read that the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees</hi> had any such fat plundring times to shew themselves as these had: I do not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eak this to accuse them, for it is known openly before <hi>God</hi> and the World; neither do I say it to discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them and cast them down, for they are low enough already; but I s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y it to the end they may repent, <hi>and give glory to God</hi> by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king known what horror of Conscience they have now, and by it prevent the generations to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121320:28"/> come, that they fall not into such folly, and that they may become glorious Saints (as they said they were) by their repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and though they doubtless shall find the mercies of God in abundance, yet they must look for a severe outward punishment from the <hi>Lord,</hi> who will by no means clear the <hi>guilty,</hi> for by their deeds they have given the enemies cause to blaspheme <hi>the Word of God,</hi> which they took to be their Rule.</p>
            <p>But of all other Sects there is none so disor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly as the Quakers; they take upon them blasphemously to be the seed of <hi>God,</hi> yet have not so much in them as common civility: The beasts of the field, by the instinct of Nature, honour their Superiours, (in their order) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the excellency of their strength, but these proud impudent Quakers glory in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than to despise <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dignities,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Jude</hi> 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>They dare stand bolt-up-right before their <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nobles,</hi> without so much civility as once to move their hats, when presumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and peremptorily they discourse with <hi>His Majesty,</hi> being admitted to have such favour to try them.</p>
            <p>Whereas <hi>Abraham, the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> seed of <hi>God,</hi> in whom <hi>all the Nations of the earth are blessed, Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.18. speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Ephron</hi> and his People, <hi>bowed himself a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121320:29"/> and again before them,</hi> yet <hi>Abraham</hi> was a mighty Prince, <hi>a Prince of God,</hi> as they call him, and as you have it in the Margin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.6, 7, 12. and <hi>Jacob bowed himself seven times to Esau</hi> his elder brother, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.3.</p>
            <p>Now if these Quakers were <hi>the children of Abraham,</hi> (as our Saviour saith, <hi>John</hi> 8.39.) <hi>they would do the works of Abraham:</hi> and I am sure if they be not <hi>Abrahams</hi> seed, they are none of Gods seed, <hi>for all are blessed in Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.18.</p>
            <p>And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> first saluted the <hi>Elders,</hi> and then declared what God had done by his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.18, 19. here we see Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> practice was to salute men, and specially being now before the Court of <hi>James Bishop of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem, Acts</hi> 21.17, 18, 19. doth salute them.</p>
            <p>Besides, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and the rest of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, accordingly touching this point, doth charge the Christians to salute one another, and to kiss one another, (which a man cannot do with his hat on) as you see in the conclusions of most of their Epistles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.19, 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12, 13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.21, 22. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.15. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.25. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.19, 21. <hi>Titus</hi> 3.15. <hi>Philem.</hi> 23.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13, 14. 2 <hi>John</hi> 13. 3 <hi>John</hi> 14. I think here is enough to reform the Quakers, (touching this point) if they be men, or were not more void of Reason than bruit beasts; for if they were the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121320:29"/> seed of God (as they vainly boast) they would follow the Children of God, and the Father <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heard say, that such a priviledge as the Quakers claim, was once given to <hi>Korsygedol</hi> in <hi>Merionethshire</hi> by King <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh, for <hi>Henry</hi> then Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> being hunted by that Tyrant <hi>Richard</hi> 3. went to <hi>Walsh,</hi> and lived with Mr. <hi>William Vechan Korsygedol</hi> a certain time, and <hi>Henry</hi> being afterward <hi>King,</hi> when Mr. <hi>Vechan Korsygedol</hi> saying he had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, would take no other gifts from him, the <hi>King</hi> compelled him to take this, <hi>That his house should be free, even his seed, to stand with their hats on in the Kings presence:</hi> and King <hi>Henry</hi> the seventh did never suffer the said <hi>William Vechan</hi> to stand bare-headed before him. Now if the Quakers can derive themselves from that <hi>honourable houfe,</hi> they may have some plea for themselves; otherwise I know no plea for them; and I think none of that House are Quakers, they hate such disorderly foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</p>
            <p>And now the Presbyters and Sectaries would fain set their former Tragedy on foot, to be act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over again; for they begin to quarrel with that worthy Bishop <hi>Wren</hi> upon the old account, that is, because he sought to bring them to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in the right way, and with more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence than they can afford: They had him in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121320:30"/> the Tower of <hi>London</hi> these 18. years, yet God would not suffer them to hurt him; and now God hath vindicated and delivered him: do they think to fight against God and prevail? they shall know that the Rules of Bishop <hi>Wren</hi> (which they despise) will be so owned of God, that all Nations shall observe it, and <hi>Rome</hi> it self shall not prevail against it.</p>
            <p>The Sectaries have reprinted their old Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles against Bishop <hi>Wren,</hi> to stir up the people to Rebellion, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.50. <hi>Acts</hi> 14.2. and one <hi>Henry Jesse,</hi> a great Sectary, hath put forth a book of lying wonders, to fulfil what is written, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11, 12. and to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then his wicked brethren; in which book is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny blind letters and stories of Frogs, and killing of people for their sakes.</p>
            <p>Truly I believe the Devil will do what he can for them, as far as God permits him, he can kill men, and bring up Frogs, and do more than all that, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.7. <hi>Job</hi> 1.19. And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less there is abundance of Witches among the Sectaries, yea some, as it is reported, before <hi>Authority,</hi> have professed and said, <hi>that they worshipped the Devil:</hi> Therefore such mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles as <hi>Henry Jesse</hi> brings forth, are Jugling, Lying, Devilish miracles; for the true miracles of <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> were to heal the sick, raise the dead, and alwayes doing <hi>good;</hi> and for all they were persecuted, we do
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121320:30"/> not read that any of their Persecutors dyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: and by such good works of healing, God beareth witness to our <hi>King</hi> also.</p>
            <p>All the Sectaries, which last year were at en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity among themselves, can now joyn and be friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to withstand <hi>the Kings Majesty and Gods Church,</hi> as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> were made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riends when they withstood the <hi>Son of God, Luke</hi> 22.12. and forasmuch that His Majesty granted them liberty to <hi>meet,</hi> and that they use their liberty for a cloak of maliciousness, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. against His Majesties Parliament and the Church, as it is evident by that book of <hi>Henry Jesse,</hi> and the <hi>Quaeraes</hi> of late scattered abroad, which strikes at <hi>King, Parliament</hi> and <hi>Church:</hi> I say, is it not just, that upon this their malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doing, (before they go any further) that His Majesty should withdraw his <hi>Acts of grace</hi> from them, and put forth a sharp Proclamation to prohibit their meetings, and command them to come to Church; and speedily to cut off his Fathers Murtherers, for I cannot see how His Majesties foresaid <hi>white Throne</hi> can be establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, until that <hi>Royal</hi> and <hi>Loyal bloud</hi> be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that cries loud to <hi>God</hi> from under the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10. now His Majesty having <hi>the sword of God</hi> for to revenge it justly, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease <hi>the wrath of God,</hi> which cannot be done without the said <hi>innocent bloud</hi> be revenged, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>and that His Majesty and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121320:31"/> judge them according to their works, and according to the wickedness of their endeavours,</hi> Psalm 28.4. <hi>and give them double according to their works,</hi> Rev. 18.6.</p>
            <p>And therefore His Majesty and Parliament should make them take the Oath of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and order it so, that whosoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he be that will not take the said Oaths, should not have the benefit of the <hi>Kings Laws;</hi> for did they not put an unlawful Engagement upon His Majesties Subjects to the same <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose?</hi> therefore it is just in His Majesty to do the same: Neither can His Majesty be <hi>justified</hi> otherwise, <hi>now</hi> they slight <hi>His Acts of grace of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to them,</hi> and speak evil of Him; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they would shew Him no mercy if they had Him and His in their power, <hi>and no mercy should be shewed to such cruel merciless people, James</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>God</hi> was gracious to <hi>England</hi> in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us some moderate men to oversway and temper the fury of the Adversaries, so that they could not have their will, else much more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief had been done; for if <hi>Harrison</hi> and his party had got the power, he dealt had with <hi>Eng.</hi> as he dealt with them which he murdered at <hi>Bazing-house,</hi> after he had given them <hi>quarter;</hi> which bloud crieth up to <hi>heaven</hi> to be avenged on him, being betrayed by his <hi>lying tongue,</hi> and then murdered by his <hi>bloudy hands:</hi> Therefore
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121320:31"/> shall that party <hi>trapan</hi> one another, and by them whom they most <hi>confide</hi> in shall they be betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and drawn into <hi>snares</hi> as a beast for the slaughter, till they are consumed from off the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>The Sectaries a while ago called <hi>Harrison</hi> their little <hi>David:</hi> Truly little indeed, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like <hi>David:</hi> and after they had great hopes in <hi>Lambert,</hi> looking upon him to be their <hi>Lamb</hi> that should stand upon <hi>Mount Sion</hi> for them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.1. but last <hi>April</hi> being at the <hi>Mount</hi> he could not get that number of soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers which he expected, for <hi>the hundred forty and four thousand</hi> stood up in the <hi>Mount</hi> with our glorious <hi>King Charles,</hi> and therefor <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> came quickly down from the <hi>Mount;</hi> and now their hope is in <hi>Henry Jesse,</hi> he is their <hi>David</hi> because <hi>David</hi> was the son of <hi>Jesse,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.12. and their great hope now is in the said <hi>Jesse</hi> according to <hi>Isa.</hi> 11.1, 10. but they shall find their <hi>Jesse</hi> to be a false <hi>Jesse,</hi> and that <hi>Jesus is the man who appeareth eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in King Charles,</hi> which if they were not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully blind they might see it.</p>
            <p>But methinks these people should look a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle upon the wisdom of the <hi>Ancients</hi> of our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that feared God, and not prefer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves before them; whose <hi>Books,</hi> in regard of their excellent knowledge and holy life, these Youngsters are not worthy to carry after them;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121320:32"/> for they, by a divine ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>spiratoin of God, could tell above a thousand years ago what we have seen done before our eyes, namely, the great Transactions that were among us, and shew the very time of our <hi>glorious Kings</hi> Restauration; when indeed our new self-wise Generation (that despise them) are so ignorant, that they cannot tell to day what shall be to morrow: <hi>The secret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will shew them his Covenant, Psal.</hi> 25.14. I believe our despised <hi>Merlins</hi> were them <hi>that feared the Lord,</hi> for they knew his secret.</p>
            <p>I know the English Chronicles, through the ignorance of the Historians, do disgrace our chief <hi>princely Merlin,</hi> and to take off that asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion I shall shew you his noble Descent, and the cause of your English Writers ignorance, in saying, <hi>Merlin had no father, but was begot by an evil spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to vindicate <hi>Merlin,</hi> the truth is, about the year of Christ 446. one <hi>Vortigerne</hi> a Nobleman, through treachery got the King <hi>Constantius</hi> to be murdered, and by his policy gets to Reign; the said Usurper and Tyrant thus ascending the <hi>throne,</hi> the murdered Kings brethren, <hi>Aurel. Ambrosius</hi> and <hi>Utherpendragon</hi> by names, with many more noble <hi>Britains,</hi> fled into <hi>Britain</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> now after they had been there some small time, <hi>Aurelius Ambrosius,</hi> who was <hi>King</hi> by right, in a disguised manner
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121320:32"/> came over sea into <hi>Wales,</hi> and hearing that a Princess, daughter to a King of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly designed for him) was gone to a Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at a place in <hi>South-Wales,</hi> now called <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marthine,</hi> whereupon <hi>Aurelius Ambrosius</hi> the King went there, and must needs see the said <hi>Lady.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>governours</hi> of the <hi>house</hi> being much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it, yet at last looking upon him as their <hi>lawfull King,</hi> consented to his demand: And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it, so that <hi>alwaies</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> was to come to the said <hi>Lady,</hi> all her fellow Nuns were called away to other <hi>Rooms;</hi> and she being alone, the <hi>King</hi> was let in unto her, till at last <hi>He</hi> prevailed with <hi>her,</hi> and begot <hi>Merthin</hi> or <hi>Merlin,</hi> as ye have it in English.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Lady</hi> knew not what he was that came to <hi>her,</hi> only he seemed to be a fine <hi>young man;</hi> but she proved to be with Child and brought forth <hi>a Man Child,</hi> and the <hi>governours</hi> that knew who was his Father, called his name <hi>Merthin Ambrosius,</hi> which in English is the <hi>marrow</hi> of the <hi>Man Ambrosius:</hi> The said <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin</hi> was born in <hi>Carmarthen,</hi> (which Town is call'd by his name to this day,) and was brought up in <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>God gave him such gifts that he was the wonder of the world;</hi> and because his <hi>Wisdom</hi> was so exceeding <hi>great,</hi> and his <hi>Birth</hi> and Parentage so <hi>obscure,</hi> the <hi>Britains</hi> thought him to be a good <hi>Angel</hi> sent to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121320:33"/> them: And the <hi>Saxons</hi> thought him to be an evil <hi>Angel</hi> sent against them; thus they could not believe him to be <hi>a Man,</hi> as indeed he was <hi>a Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Vortigerne</hi> the tyrant being full of fear (as all traytors are,) sends workmen to build him a strong <hi>Castle</hi> at a place he had made choice of near the Sea in <hi>South-walsh:</hi> But as they began to build, nothing would <hi>stand</hi> there, for what they built in the day was thrown down in the <hi>night.</hi> And <hi>Vortigerne</hi> being vexed at it, sent for all the <hi>Barthes</hi> and <hi>Wise men</hi> to come before <hi>him:</hi> And he threatned them, <hi>saying,</hi> if they could not tell him how to prevent the throwing down of his <hi>building,</hi> he would put them to <hi>death;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Barthes</hi> told him, that he must find out <hi>a Man Child</hi> that had no <hi>Father,</hi> and take his <hi>bloud</hi> to water the <hi>foundation</hi> of his <hi>building,</hi> after that his <hi>build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> should go forward and stand.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Vortigerne</hi> sent out scouts all about the <hi>Land</hi> to seek for such <hi>a Child,</hi> and some of them coming to <hi>Carmarthen,</hi> as a company of youths played by the high-way, one of the youths falling out with <hi>Merlin,</hi> said, thou art <hi>a stripling</hi> and hast no Father, the <hi>scouts</hi> hearing that took <hi>Merlin</hi> and his <hi>mother,</hi> and brought them before <hi>Vortigerne,</hi> and he examined the <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>Merlin,</hi> and she told him how it was; that she being a <hi>Virgin</hi> in such a place, a fair
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121320:33"/> young <hi>man</hi> in appearance came to her alwaies when her fellows were absent, and at last over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came her with <hi>Love,</hi> and that was <hi>her Sons Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> and she intreated him to save her <hi>Sons</hi> life: saying, he though but <hi>young,</hi> was wiser then all his <hi>Barthes</hi> and <hi>Wise men,</hi> and <hi>a holy Child.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>Vortigerne</hi> seeing <hi>Merlin</hi> had no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to hurt him, for he was of such a <hi>lovely</hi> sweet countenance full of <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> And he to try his Wisdom asked what was the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> his building would not <hi>stand?</hi> said <hi>Merlin,</hi> the <hi>Rock</hi> upon which you <hi>build</hi> is hollow <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,</hi> and there are two <hi>Caves</hi> in it, one on each side, and there are two great <hi>Dragons</hi> in the <hi>Caves</hi> which meet every night in the hollow of the <hi>Rock;</hi> and fighting shakes the <hi>building</hi> so that it falls: But in the day while the <hi>builders</hi> are there making a noise, they do not stir out of the <hi>Caves;</hi> but now dig deeper until you come to the firm botom of the <hi>Rock,</hi> and lay your <hi>Foundation</hi> thereupon, and besure your <hi>build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> will not fall: Whereupon <hi>Vortigerne</hi> did as <hi>Merlin</hi> counselled him, and found all true, so the <hi>Castle</hi> was built.</p>
            <p>Thus by <hi>Gods providence Merlin</hi> was brought before <hi>Vortigerne,</hi> and became <hi>great</hi> with him, and <hi>Merlin</hi> by his <hi>wisdom</hi> did so defeat the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and dishearten him by his Prophesie, that at last <hi>Aurelius Ambrosius,</hi> with his brother
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121320:34"/>
               <hi>Utherpendragon,</hi> came over sea, and quickly had a great Army, and burned <hi>Vortigerne</hi> in the said <hi>castle</hi> which he had <hi>built,</hi> when he had tyranniz'd near upon 40. years, and had done a world of mischief to the <hi>Church,</hi> and to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nation:</hi> and <hi>Aurelius Ambrosius</hi> reigned in his stead.</p>
            <p>Here you see who was <hi>Merlin Ambrosius</hi> his <hi>father</hi> and <hi>mother,</hi> where he was <hi>born,</hi> and how he came to <hi>Vortigerne;</hi> now methinks his very name and the time which he lived in should have informed our <hi>Historians,</hi> and shewed them <hi>Merthins</hi> father, and that there is great reason why it was concealed then, his father being a banished King, that du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st not be known to have been in the Land, for if it had been known many had dyed for it; and his mother a Nun of great repute: and indeed <hi>Carmarthin</hi> should have told them where <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin</hi> or <hi>Merlin,</hi> as they call him, was born, and that he was not born at <hi>Maltborow,</hi> as some would have it to be the place of his birth. So much for <hi>Merlin Ambrosius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to our <hi>Wisemen of Gotham</hi> again: The <hi>Quakers</hi> give out, forsooth, that they will not rebel nor <hi>fight,</hi> when indeed the last year, and all along the <hi>War,</hi> the Army was full of them; there is no truth in the Sectaries, as to that point, for if they have liberty to meet and increase till they get a considerable party, you
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121320:34"/> shall find that they will strive to be masters of all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Puritans, Anabaptists</hi> and <hi>Brownists</hi> to my knowledge said, <hi>It was not lawful for them to resist the Kings power;</hi> but they, finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves strong enough for Him, stick not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say it again; and they resist Him in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t degree, but it will be in vain for them now to <hi>strive,</hi> for whosoever he be that stands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>King and Church of England</hi> shall be destroyed, so saith <hi>the Word of God</hi> to me, and our <hi>Merlins</hi> do witness it also; therefore let <hi>Fox</hi> the Quaker not glory in his foolishness, for it will come to nothing, all such bubbles blown up in the air, (as Children use in their play) will fall to the <hi>earth</hi> and be seen no more, for though they bark they cannot bite.</p>
            <p>And what exceeding madness is it for any to withstand such a <hi>King,</hi> that by the <hi>Word of God</hi> is so shewed <hi>beforehand</hi> in Prophesies and Promises, and His birth witnessed by a <hi>Day-star,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.28. (yea, and many hundred saw it) to shew the <hi>world</hi> that <hi>Christ</hi> in him appeareth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. besides the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> that is full for it, there are abundance of modern Prophesies that doe also wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness it.</p>
            <p>Again, see how <hi>God</hi> (as I may say so with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence) contrived the year of <hi>His Nativity,</hi> to be compleat according to the holy <hi>Scripture</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121320:35"/> and our <hi>Merlins sayings;</hi> for if the <hi>King</hi> had been 31. or 29. when He came to the <hi>throne,</hi> then he could not have been that <hi>David</hi> spoken of, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.23, 24. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.24. <hi>Hos.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Pughs</hi> book <hi>pag.</hi> 76. and if He had not come in at 1660. then he could not have been that <hi>Owen</hi> which the <hi>Merlin</hi> speaks of in <hi>Pughs</hi> book, <hi>pag.</hi> 87. <hi>pag.</hi> 86.</p>
            <p>But <hi>God</hi> brings in the <hi>King</hi> according to the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> and our <hi>Merlins sayings,</hi> for he comes in at 1660. and in the 30. year of His <hi>age,</hi> agreeable to the holy <hi>Scripture</hi> touching <hi>Joseph, Gen.</hi> 41.46. <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Jesus, Luke</hi> 3.23. and last of all <hi>Charles</hi> under the name of <hi>Owen, Pughs</hi> book <hi>pag.</hi> 76. all four co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming personally at 30. years of age to exercise their power and authority, and agreeable to our <hi>Merlins</hi> he comes in at 1660.</p>
            <p>Methinks the harmony of the <hi>holy Scripture</hi> with our modern Prophesies, and the <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> coming of <hi>King Charles</hi> in accordingly, 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.7, 8, 9, 10. should convert you Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, seeing you profess to have knowledge in divine mysteries: sure if you see not now, <hi>doubtless</hi> ye are blinded with vain <hi>conceits;</hi> and if you do not say to <hi>King Charles</hi> as the People said to <hi>Cyrus, Isa.</hi> 45.13, 14. <hi>Surely God is in thee,</hi> you will be shut up <hi>in darkness for ever, Jude</hi> 13. and so be it, if you will not receive the <hi>truth</hi> and be saved, and not make work for the Hangman.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121320:35"/>
            <p>Yet you believe you have the same game to play as you had in 1641. and so forward, <hi>do not you believe that:</hi> for then the <hi>King</hi> had no Army, and the People were <hi>foolish</hi> and wanton through over-much prosperity; but now the <hi>King</hi> hath an Army on foot, under such <hi>noble Commanders</hi> as hate your <hi>whimsical way</hi> of <hi>preaching,</hi> or rather <hi>prating;</hi> and the people having <hi>smarted</hi> for such things, they are grown <hi>wiser</hi> than to believe you; therefore the best way for you is to wheel to the <hi>right,</hi> and as you were Protestants come to the <hi>Church of England</hi> again, and there you will find rest for your <hi>souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have spoken largely touching these Presbyters and Sectaries, whose persons I love, but I hate their evil wayes: I shall speak a word to You, <hi>Most glorious Parliament,</hi> saying, Beware of upholding the Presbyterian or Sectarian Interest, lest any of you fall <hi>by it;</hi> you know what fruit you had heretofore from it, and how the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> was <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphosed by it:</hi> More especially I speak to you, sometimes called the <hi>secluded Members,</hi> you have done the most glorious work of all (in opening the way to Peace) when you first sate after your <hi>seclusion;</hi> O do not you lose your <hi>reward</hi> by your <hi>standing for</hi> the aforesaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terests.</p>
            <p>And I beseech you all, most <hi>Honourable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121320:36"/> to be united and agree together as one man, to settle the <hi>Kings Majesty</hi> and His <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> in the good old way, as it was in the beginning of <hi>Englands</hi> trouble▪ There is talk of an <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> to come forth from you, to exempt some persons and punish o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; all being equally <hi>guilty,</hi> that in my judgment is partiality, which will have a <hi>bad</hi> consequence: Save none that are guilty of murder, but deliver them up to the former Laws made by <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> that is a just and a sure way; for how can you in Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice <hi>quit</hi> them, that murdered those which stood for <hi>God, King</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> and not bring that righteous bloud upon your own <hi>heads,</hi> and take the Murderers <hi>guilt</hi> upon you?</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Honours</hi> see how cruel I am to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, and Why? because I find by their 37. <hi>Quaeraes</hi> how cruel they are against <hi>His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty</hi> and <hi>Your Honours,</hi> for all the <hi>King</hi> is so merciful unto them: I thought to have written altogether for them, that <hi>Your Honours</hi> would be merciful to them as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if you will make an Act of Oblivion to save any, save all and be clean, for God is full of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: You know touching the plague of Leprosie,</hi> Levit. 13.12, 13. <hi>if a man hath it upon any part of his body, the</hi> Priest <hi>must pronounce him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean; but if a man hath it all over his body, then the</hi> Priest <hi>must pronounce him clean; Now the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121320:36"/> case is the same; Your Honours look upon a part of the Nation to be guilty of the late famous Kings bloud, but if you exactly go according to the Laws of</hi> England, <hi>you shall find the whole body of the Nation is guilty of his bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now his Majesty wisely weighing this, for the peace of the Nation, hath engaged Himself in the</hi> Word of a King, <hi>to pardon all that come in to Him, (with a reference thus to Your Honours) except some few persons that Your Honours shall think fit to exempt from pardon, in regard of their hands being deep in the late Kings bloud; for the bonds of natural affection (yet contrary to His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mind) binds</hi> His Royal Majesty, <hi>so that he could do no less than seek some satisfaction for His Royal Fathers bloud, and therefore the burthen lieth now upon Your Honours shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And partiality is to have respect to Persons in judgment,</hi> James 2.4. <hi>The late</hi> King <hi>you know, hath to his everlasting glory before God and the World forgiven his enemies; and would have our present</hi> King <hi>not to study revenge on them, this is sufficiently made out in His late</hi> Majesties <hi>last Speech to our present</hi> King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But these Lords,</hi> Derby, Strafford, Bishop Laud, Hamilton, Holland, Capell, Montrosse; <hi>and many more great Persons that suffered for the same cause, gave no such order to their Sons or friends: Now If Your honours require bloud for
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121320:37"/> the late Kings bloud, who indeed would have no bloud spilt for him; and by your Act shut out the other great families from having justice against those that murdered their Fathers and Friends, it will cause heart-burning of a dangerous conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And our late</hi> K. Charles <hi>of famous memory did foresee all this: Therefore it is one cause why he would have our present</hi> King Charles <hi>to pardon all, but it is fitter Your</hi> Honours <hi>should quit them then His</hi> Majesty, <hi>and for any thing that I know it is referred to You for that End. Then all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovesaid Families in reason, cannot but content themselves with such an Act as well as his</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty; <hi>though it be all Mercy and no Equity, I break forth my judgement to Your</hi> Honours, <hi>if my mite may adde any thing to Your Information, I am not for bloud-shed, yet I would have their Purses a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> empty as mine is; and that with a ruined Conscience, is as bad as the</hi> Popes Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, <hi>if not worse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now I am against them, seeing no Reason that I should stand for them; being they stand against the <hi>King, Parliament and Nation.</hi> The Sectaries now urge upon us, that we have taken the Scottish Covenant: What if we have? we are not bound to keep it; for according to <hi>Englands Lawes,</hi> there is nothing <hi>binding</hi> to us, but what is done by <hi>King, Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121320:37"/>
            <p>The theeves at Newgate enter into <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> amongst themselves, and make it as firm as any <hi>Covenant</hi> can be; suppose an honest man be forced to take that <hi>Covenant,</hi> Sectaries, will you say that he must needs keep it? or in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son must you not confess that <hi>Covenant</hi> to be a vain thing done without true <hi>Authority,</hi> and that <hi>a man</hi> ought not to keep it?</p>
            <p>The theeves <hi>Authority</hi> is as authentick, as the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Scots Covenanters:</hi> Nay rather more <hi>authentick,</hi> for the <hi>King</hi> heares no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Newgates <hi>Covenant</hi> when it is made, therefore he saith nothing against it; but the <hi>King</hi> declared against the <hi>Scots Covenant</hi> all along to His dying day: Therefore it hath not so good <hi>Authority</hi> as the theeves <hi>Covenant</hi> hath, and the ends of both their <hi>Covenants</hi> are alike, tending to rob and destroy <hi>the Kings loyal Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope this manifestation is sufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy that work of the devil, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8. and to disoblige every <hi>Soul</hi> that took the <hi>Scots Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> from fear of breaking it, for doubtlesse the <hi>Scots Covenant,</hi> and such is that called, <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>A Covenant with Death and agreement with Hell, which the Lord doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to disanull;</hi> which if Your <hi>Honours</hi> read the said <hi>Scripture,</hi> you will see the Raign of the Sectaries and their Ruine: Therefore hasten to Ruine them accordingly, and so fulfil the said Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121320:38"/>
            <p>And let his Excellency noble General <hi>Monck,</hi> the <hi>Honourable</hi> secluded Members, and the <hi>Royal City of London,</hi> take heed they never fall into the hands of the <hi>Sectaries;</hi> for I am sure nothing troubleth the <hi>Sectaries</hi> more, then that they did not, (when they had power) destroy them all (last year) and burn the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> because under <hi>God,</hi> the City, <hi>Monck,</hi> and the said Members were made so instrumentall to bring <hi>His Majesty</hi> upon them, and all the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> beware you fall not into their hands again; they will pay you because you were for <hi>Kingship,</hi> and destroy you also.</p>
            <p>And when I told their Commanders many times at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> that <hi>His Majesty</hi> should come in. They answered me saying, <hi>let him come in when he please, rather then he shall have it, we will destroy</hi> London <hi>and every place; so that he shall have but little left him.</hi> (This was their resolution,) I answered them saying from these Texts, 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15. <hi>That</hi> His Majesty <hi>should come in like a Thief in the night, and they should not destroy as they though to do:</hi> Nay said they we shall watch him for that.</p>
            <p>And now their <hi>watch</hi> is broke up, Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours had need to <hi>watch,</hi> for <hi>Praise-God-Barbone</hi> the Leather-seller in <hi>Fleetstreet</hi> is very brisk, which <hi>signifieth</hi> to me, that the Sectaries have some <hi>design</hi> on foot, that ministreth great <hi>hopes</hi> unto them: <hi>Behold I warn you of it aforehand,</hi> Ezek. 3.17.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121320:38"/>
            <p>And Your <hi>Honours</hi> differing, and deferring the <hi>act of Oblivion</hi> may be of great advantage to the Sectaries, for all the Land is full of fear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that <hi>act</hi> come out, because honest precious men (as well as the vile that did it voluntary,) were forced to take up Armes, pay Taxes, and bear Offices under the Rebels against the <hi>King;</hi> and they are afraid they shall be called to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for it, which fear may cause them to joyn with the Sectaries and rise against <hi>Your Honours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the only way <hi>to take the precious from the vile,</hi> Jer. 15.19. And to prevent their rising against Your <hi>Honours,</hi> is speedily to make an <hi>act;</hi> that all which shall take the Oathes of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> is pardoned for these crimes: <hi>Namely,</hi> taking up Armes, paying Taxes, bearing Offices for the Rebels against the <hi>King;</hi> and that all those which were assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants to bring <hi>His Majesty</hi> to <hi>His Throne,</hi> (be their <hi>Crimes</hi> nere so great) is pardoned also, <hi>but expresse none by name;</hi> and that those which will not take the said <hi>Oathes,</hi> to be declared Rebels, that shall not enjoy the benefit of the <hi>Law</hi> to protect them.</p>
            <p>And for you <hi>Quakers,</hi> which think it a sin to take the said <hi>Oathes,</hi> our <hi>Saviour, Mat.</hi> 5.34. forbids not such <hi>Oathes</hi> as are tendred by his <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> unto men for their own good; but he <hi>forbids</hi> all other <hi>Oathes</hi> commonly used by <hi>swearers</hi> upon small occasions, and in common<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121320:39"/> talk, and so doth the <hi>Apostle</hi> Jam. 5.12. <hi>for God himself (upon great occasions) swore many time to confirm his promise to his people,</hi> Heb. 6.16, 17. Psalm 110.4. and Ezek. 33.10, 11. <hi>As I live saith the Lord God, I have no pleasure in the death of the wicked; but that the wicked turn from his way and live,</hi> and the <hi>Angel sware</hi> Rev. 10.5, 6. And our Saviour <hi>Himself</hi> upon great occasion to confirm the Truth, used to say, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily verily I say unto you,</hi> these words of <hi>Christ</hi> are no small <hi>engagement</hi> if not an <hi>Oath,</hi> as some affirm it to be an <hi>Oath;</hi> thus you see an Oath upon great occasion is not sin, <hi>for God himself doth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>King</hi> will not punish you, nor <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid</hi> your meetings for not taking the <hi>Oathes:</hi> if you take them not, it is nothing to him; you hurt your selves by it: for be sure <hi>Masters of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> will destroy you, rather than you shall meet to <hi>seduce</hi> their children and servants; and when you complain to the <hi>King</hi> he will not hear you, nor have any thing to do with you, you are none of his Subjects, any body may kill you, and take all from you, and not be questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, you must not have the benefit of the <hi>Law;</hi> if you were strangers, then the <hi>King</hi> ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you whatsoever your Tenets were, so that you did not wrong his people; but being Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and will not obey your <hi>King,</hi> your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition will be worse than the beasts of the field.</p>
            <p>And now most Royal <hi>Soveraign,</hi> I am come
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121320:39"/> to Your <hi>Majesty</hi> again; beseeching Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> to pardon my <hi>Rudeness</hi> of speech: for I have (as many more have) so long conversed with Rebells, that I know not how to frame <hi>a loyall speech</hi> aright, though I endeavour to do it, and my further request to Your <hi>Majesty</hi> is, that you stir up the gift of <hi>God</hi> that is in you, which was given You by <hi>Prophesie,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.14. 2 Tim. 1.6. <hi>Be strong and of good courage,</hi> Josh. 1.5, 6, 7. <hi>and observe the Lawes of</hi> England.</p>
            <p>It is faid that when the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>King Cyrus</hi> what the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> had Prophesied of <hi>King Cyrus,</hi> about 200. yeares before he was born; that he should let the Captive <hi>Jewes</hi> go and build <hi>Jerusalem</hi> and the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> Isa. 44.28. Isa. 45. <hi>King Cyrus rejoyced, and immediately he made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, to send the</hi> Jewes <hi>withall speed to do it accordingly,</hi> Ezra 1.1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh King,</hi> there are more <hi>Prophesies</hi> of Your <hi>Majesty</hi> then can be held forth to You, and of thousands of yeares standing: <hi>King Cyrus</hi> was but a Type of Your <hi>Majesty,</hi> and now do you build our <hi>Jerusalm,</hi> and build you the House of <hi>God</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and do you enquire what <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> remaine, and send them to the work: <hi>The charge is upon Your Majesty,</hi> and <hi>King Cyrus</hi> understood it so, as ye see <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.2, 3, 4. <hi>Let no Presbyt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nian have a hand in building Gods House, and let them not hinder the building of it.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121320:40"/> Your</hi> Majesty may see them plainly set out, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. <hi>Let it be done up as it was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was destroyed:</hi> That is, as <hi>Bishop Laud,</hi> (by Your Royal <hi>Fathers</hi> command) ordered it, and as <hi>Bishop Wren,</hi> by the same command put it in practise; <hi>For the House of God which Your Royal Father and Bishop Laud hath sealed with their bloud, may not be altered in form nor fashion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Most glorious Soveraign,</hi> Consider that hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>Crime</hi> of <hi>Harrison,</hi> exceeds all the <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> evil actions: For Your Royall <hi>Father,</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Gentrie that suffered, did not expect mercy from their enemies, because they agree not with them; but at <hi>Bazing-house</hi> the <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>Harrison</hi> agreed upon <hi>quarter,</hi> and he delivered himself and all accordingly into <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons</hi> hands, now for <hi>Harison</hi> when he had dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed him <hi>blasphemously</hi> to say these words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10. <hi>Cursed be he that doth the work of the Lord deceitfully,</hi> and with that killed the Captain, was such a work of the Devil, that the like was never heard of; for <hi>Harrison,</hi> if he were not an ignorant Devil, might have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood, that the work of the Lord is to keep his <hi>Word,</hi> and to save them <hi>that believe him,</hi> and that it is the work of the Devil to lie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy them <hi>that believe him,</hi> for so did <hi>Harrison</hi> destroy that <hi>Captain,</hi> which <hi>Captains</hi> bloud cries to <hi>Your Majesty</hi> for justice against him; therefore <hi>Your Majesty ought to make inquisition
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121320:40"/> for such bloud, Psal.</hi> 9.12. and destroy the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers: Yet <hi>Harrison</hi> glorieth in all his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedness, and shall he live?</p>
            <p>Now for <hi>Your Majesties</hi> judging those Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, I advise You to refer them to the former <hi>Laws</hi> made by <hi>Kings, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and for using (except for murder) Your Royal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative as King <hi>David</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 29.22. for matter of <hi>life</hi> as large as You please, I say it is good; but as touching judgment in other things do not meddle, but let the Law both <hi>ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ical</hi> and <hi>civil</hi> decide the matter, and as King <hi>Jehoshaphat</hi> did, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. do You send forth Judges, and charge them to do right in the presence of <hi>God,</hi> for what is mercy to one may be cruelty to another; therefore <hi>let Justice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide it,</hi> and for those that have been Instruments to restore Your <hi>Majesty</hi> and the Law, let all their former misdemeanors be buried in oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they deserve <hi>Your Majesties</hi> favour, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom I hope to have a portion of <hi>Your Majesties</hi> favour also.</p>
            <p>Blessed be God, <hi>Your Majesty</hi> is come to the Throne, yet <hi>Your Majesties</hi> poor friends, that suffered for You and the Law, have little or no relief, but the rich enemies triumph and abound in prosperity, having Yours and Your <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi> Loyal Subjects Estates in their hands as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which if it continue so, doubtless they will seek the preheminence again, to the endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121320:41"/> of Your <hi>Majesty</hi> and Your friends: Therefore it is necessary for <hi>Your Majesties</hi> safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that You and every one have their own again speedily, as <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.14. <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.28. there was no <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> used with <hi>Solomon</hi> when he dispatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his great enemies, and then the Kingdom was established in his hand, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.46.</p>
            <p>And now to conclude, praying for <hi>Your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Majesty</hi> and the noble <hi>Dukes</hi> Your Brothers, with Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> words, saying, <hi>For this cause I bow my knees unto the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, of whom the whole Family in heaven and earth is named, that he would grant You, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the riches of his glory, to be strengthened with might by his spirit in the inner man, that Christ may dwell in Your hearts by Faith, that ye being rooted and grounded in love, may be able to comprehend with all Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height, and to know the love of Christ which passeth knowledge, that ye might be filled with all the fulness of God: Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly above all that we can ask or think, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power that worketh in us, unto him be glory in the Church by Christ Jesus, throughout all Ages world without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majesties Loyal Subject, <hi>Arise Evans.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my House near the Kings Play-house in <hi>Black-friers,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>August</hi> 20. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>